<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Currus triumphalis, è terebinthô, or, An account of the many admirable vertues of oleum terebinthinæ more particularly, of the good effects produced by its application to recent wounds, especially with respect to the hemorrhagies of the veins, and arteries, and the no less pernicious weepings of the nerves, and lymphaducts : wherein also, the common methods, and medicaments, used to restrain hemorrhagies, are examined, and divers of them censured : and lastly, a new way of amputation, and a speedier convenient method of curing stumps, than that commonly practised, is with divers other useful matters recommended to the military chirurgeon, in two letters : the one to his most honoured, James Pearse, Esq, chirurgeon to His Royal Highness the Duke of York, and chirurgeon general to His Majestie's Navy Royal : the other, to Mr. Thomas Hobbs, chirurgeon in London / by James Yonge.</title>
            <author>Yonge, James, 1647-1721.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1679</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 197 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 77 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A67811</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing Y39</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R38786</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">18112315</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 18112315</idno>
            <idno type="VID">106833</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A67811)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 106833)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1113:20)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Currus triumphalis, è terebinthô, or, An account of the many admirable vertues of oleum terebinthinæ more particularly, of the good effects produced by its application to recent wounds, especially with respect to the hemorrhagies of the veins, and arteries, and the no less pernicious weepings of the nerves, and lymphaducts : wherein also, the common methods, and medicaments, used to restrain hemorrhagies, are examined, and divers of them censured : and lastly, a new way of amputation, and a speedier convenient method of curing stumps, than that commonly practised, is with divers other useful matters recommended to the military chirurgeon, in two letters : the one to his most honoured, James Pearse, Esq, chirurgeon to His Royal Highness the Duke of York, and chirurgeon general to His Majestie's Navy Royal : the other, to Mr. Thomas Hobbs, chirurgeon in London / by James Yonge.</title>
                  <author>Yonge, James, 1647-1721.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[24], 120 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for J. Martyn ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1679.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Suggests the use of oil of turpentine to arrest hemorrhage, and describes for the first time the use of a flap of tissue in amputations.</note>
                  <note>Includes, photographed at end, p. 127 of St. Bartholomew's Hospital journal (Oct., 1946) "James Yonge's 'Oleum terebinthinæ,' 1679 / by John L. Thornton", describing the contributions of this pioneering English naval surgeon; also a copy of a letter, dated 31 October 1927, advertising the sale of a copy of the work to Dr. Philip Gosse.</note>
                  <note>Errata: prelim. p. [24].</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Huntington Library.</note>
                  <note>Includes bibliographical references.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Turpentine --  Therapeutic use --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Amputation --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Surgery --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Medicine --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:106833:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:106833:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:106833:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:106833:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Currus Triumphalis, è Terebinthô.</hi> OR AN Account of the many admirable Vertues OF <hi>Oleum Terebinthinae.</hi> More particularly, of the good effects produced by its application to recent Wounds, eſpecially with reſpect to the <hi>Hemorrhagies</hi> of the Veins, and Arte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, and the no leſs pernicious weepings of the Nerves, and Lymphaducts. Wherein alſo, the common Methods, and Medicaments, uſed to reſtrain <hi>Hemorrhagies,</hi> are examined, and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers of them Cenſured. And laſtly, A new Way of Amputation, and a ſpeedier convenient Method of curing Stumps, than that com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly practiſed, is with divers other uſeful matters recommended to the Military Chirurgeon, In Two LETTERS: The one to his moſt Honoured, <hi>James Pearſe</hi> Eſq; Chi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rurgeon to His Royal Highneſs the Duke of <hi>York,</hi> and Chirurgeon General to His Majeſtie's Navy Royal. The other, to Mr. <hi>Thomas Hobbs,</hi> Chirurgeon in <hi>London.</hi>By <hi>JAMES YONGE.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>J. Martyn,</hi> Printer to the <hi>Royal Society,</hi> at the Bell in St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Church-yard. 1679.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:106833:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:106833:4"/>
            <head>TO His much Honoured JOHN KNIGHT, Eſq; Serjeant Chirurgeon to His MAJESTY.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Fter Mr. <hi>Pearſes</hi> Command and Approbation, had obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged me to make publick, what (in an accidental con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſs of ſome Chirurgeons in <hi>London</hi>) I had tranſitorily delivered, concerning the conſtrictive faculty of <hi>Oleum Tere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>binthinae:</hi> I ſoon reſolved to addreſs the reſults of my obedience to him, in a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dication to your ſelf; in which preſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ption I am become encouraged, and confirmed by many prevailing conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations:
<pb facs="tcp:106833:5"/>the principal of which is, your readineſs to undertake its Patronage, and permiſſion given me ſo to direct it: Motives not much leſs conſiderable and important, are your kind and charitable approving, what I have there delivered; the many other favours you have con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred on me; the courteſie with which at all times and occaſions, you have treated me; the competency of your Judgment, to licence and juſtifie my procedure; the eminency of your place (no mean demonſtration of your abili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties and merit. If the extraordinary in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuition of the <hi>great Maſter</hi> (eſpecially of men medically profeſſed) and your ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving ſo long ſerved him, as his perſonal Chirurgeon, be conſidered.) And laſtly, the benefit of <hi>your</hi> Countenance and Patronage, to promulgate and credit the Diſcourſe among the military Men of our Art, over whom you have ſo high an Office, and influence.</p>
            <p>Theſe, Sir, were the occaſions of my
<pb facs="tcp:106833:5"/>affixing your Name to ſo mean a trifle; and theſe are the ſentiments I have of thoſe motives: the former enforced me to this preſumption, the latter have ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liged me, thankfully to acknowledg your favours, and ever to be, <hi>Sir,</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>Plimouth,</hi> 
                  <date>July 5. 1678.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>Your moſt devoted humble Servant, <hi>JAMES YONGE.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:106833:6"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:106833:6"/>
            <head>THE PREFACE.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hough the <hi>Mercurius</hi> every Term, and the <hi>Gazette</hi> twice a week, redundantly anſwer that common enquiry of the literate, <hi>What new Books are come out:</hi> yet con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidering ſome writings of the preſent day, relating to our Art, <hi>Solomon</hi> long ſince an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticipated a ſutabler Reſponſe; <hi>There is nothing new under the Sun.</hi> Such plagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ary obſolete ſtuff as they conſiſt of, being obtruded on the World to no better uſe, than verifie a Paradox of great affinity with that of the wiſe King, <hi>Nihil dictum quod non dictum prius,</hi> juſtifying alſo his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon cenſure, <hi>they contain nothing new.</hi> Such ridiculous and eaſie thieves are their Authors, that they expoſe to publick ſale the plate, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> they ſteal, without altering what
<pb facs="tcp:106833:7"/>may diſcover it, except the name of the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prietor, in place of which they inſert their own: the only thing they can juſtly call ſo, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept the vain picture, and <hi>ordinary</hi> Title in the frontiſpiece: ſuch uncunning Pens are ſo far from obliging the World, that they become our debtors, not only for the money their books coſt, but for the time miſpent in peruſing them.</p>
            <p>That I may with equal innocency, and truth, make this reflection here, will, I hope good Reader, be manifeſt to thee, on a candid and ingenuous peruſal of the enſuing Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe, when in the moſt material part there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, thou ſhalt find things neither old, nor borrowed; ſomewhat of the laſt may have oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curred in the collateral part, (diſowned by quotation) where alſo I may have had the luck to jump with another man's Opinion, and ſenſe: but that being moſtly (if at all) in the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flections, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> to nick another man's ſenſe, is but to have his experience, when I aver it im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſsible, but the ſame inconveniencies muſt occur to his notice, and conſequently, (be he ingenious) cannot eſcape his Cenſure.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:106833:7"/>
            <p>To quit my ſelf wholly from ſtealing o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther mens Notions, or Inventions, and pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhing them as my own, there remains yet a piece of Juſtice for me to do, which relates to the ſubject <hi>Arcanum;</hi> if it be not new to the Public, my memory, or my intelligence hath failed me; that it was communicated to me ſome years ſince, by a worthy<note n="*" place="margin">Dr. <hi>J. Sprage,</hi> &amp; Dr. <hi>T. pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cer,</hi> are the perſons here inti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mated, whoſe names I reſolved to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceal, till I found my ſelf neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitated to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary, by one from whom I am ſorry and aſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive the occaſion; It's one Mr. <hi>Jinkinſon,</hi> of this Country, who (whileſt theſe papers were peruſed by ſome Ingenious men of the Faculty in <hi>London</hi>) clancular<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly &amp; diſingenuouſly inſinuated among them there, that he was not only the firſt that applied Oil of <hi>Turpentine</hi> to reſtrain the hemorrhagies of wounds, but that all the obſervations I had there written were communicated from himſelf to me; the falſhood of which arrogance I could abundantly mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt, together with the frequency of his ſo dealing not only with my ſelf, but all other of the Fraternity with whom he hath converſed in theſe parts, but I conſider of a ſufficient eviction that I inſert the true Author's name, and thus publickly accuſe him of falſhood in that pretence, as I have alſo privately done before ſome Friends, where both in word and writing he diſclaimed what in <hi>London</hi> he had aſſumed; and I do further aver that I was the firſt, and am hitherto the only man that ever uſed it after Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putations, and that this Calumniator hath not for the ſeven laſt years, <hi>i.e.</hi> ſince he knew the Secret, had opportunity ſo to do, nor (except one) any other eminent occaſion to experiment it; and although ſuch rudeneſs would juſtly raiſe higher reſentments, and force more ſevere reflections (of which few men are more capable) yet I ſhall here forbear him in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect to the reputation of our Profeſſion and him, that educated us both therein, <hi>viz.</hi> my ever honoured Mr. <hi>S. Richmond</hi> of <hi>Liverpool.</hi>
               </note> Phyſician, upon my diſmembring a Patient to us both, is my duty to acknowledg, though I conceal his name, becauſe he confeſs'd it a Secret reveal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to him by another, whoſe private and ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginal exploration it was.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:106833:8"/>
            <p>The ground of whoſe finding it, is ſo no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table, that it deſerves your notice. Some Chi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rurgeons uſing the <hi>Levant,</hi> had told him, That the <hi>Turks,</hi> as ſoon as they have ampu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tated, uſe to dip the ſtump in hot Tar, and that they thereby ſecurely reſtrained the Flux, and laid the foundation of a very good dige<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion: The way ſeeming too brutiſh and ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible to be imitated, he conſidered how to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trive it more neatly, and began to think what Medicine had affinity with Tar: none ſeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing more like it than <hi>Turpentine;</hi> he ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed that the Oil (containing in it the Bal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſam) as it was more likely to be the ſtronger digeſtive, ſo alſo it might as effectually re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrain the Flux; he accordingly experiment<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it, found it by many trials, to exceed even his hopes and expectations.</p>
            <p>The diſtinctions I have made of the ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral ways of reſtraining <hi>Hemorrhagies,</hi> to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with the reaſons, cenſures, and obje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions contained in my charge againſt them, are wholly my own: for though the number of them are exactly equal, with thoſe of fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous
<pb facs="tcp:106833:8"/>Dr. <hi>A. Read,</hi> upon the like ſubject; yet the matter of them will appear, on compari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon very different; I forbear to intimate wherein, in honour to his name, and works.</p>
            <p>The Experiments and Obſervations ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaining and confirming the operation of our celebrated Balſam, I muſt alſo own; the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer, I want time and opportunity to inlarge; the later is but a few of many more, I might produce, to verifie what I have ſaid of its ſtopping <hi>Hemorrhagies.</hi> Let it ſuffice that I never yet knew it fail.</p>
            <p>The deſign of this Publication, is to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commend to thee a cheap, common, and incom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parable Medicine that duly claims preference from all others, for the firſt dreſſings of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent Wounds, performing at once all the prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipal intentions, <hi>viz.</hi> reſtraining the <hi>Hemor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rhoea,</hi> and lachrymations, inducing digeſtion, preventing Convulſions, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> All which are not otherwiſe performed, but by different ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plications, longer time, frequent miſcarriage, and greater uncertainty.</p>
            <p>The occaſion of my thus publiſhing it, for
<pb facs="tcp:106833:9"/>the ſake of whoſe commands, and to whom you are indebted for the benefit thereof (if any ſuch thing accrew) is at large diſcovered in the beginning of the Diſcourſe.</p>
            <p>I hope my integrity in thoſe well intended endeavours, will deſerve thy charity and can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dor, of which there will be great need, becauſe many little failures and defects, muſt I know occur, (impoſſible to avoid) under the haſte, wherewith it was written, the mixture and diſturbance of other avocations, and the diſad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage of my undertaking ſo unpreſidented a work.</p>
            <p>As for the great and avowed faults, <hi>viz.</hi> the boldneſs of the attempt, the harſh, and ſeemingly unbecoming criminations, I hope thou wilt find my Apology and juſtification in the reaſons there ſuggeſted, in the Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rities there quoted, and in thy own ſenſe and apprehenſion alſo, if thou put theſe things to the teſt thereof. Not that I am inſenſible how high a preſumption, and confident an undertaking it is, for a young Country Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctitioner, to impeach, as I have done, the Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thods
<pb facs="tcp:106833:9"/>and Medicaments which preſcription hath endeared, and made familiar; though I have the vanity to preſume, I have ſubſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuted better in their room; and thereby re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compenced the rejection of thoſe more nume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous, though more fallible ones.</p>
            <p>But though I have rejected the practice, I have, and ever will be civil to the memory of the Practitioners of paſt-days, and retain a veneration for their Names: to do otherwiſe, were to anticipate a cenſure for my ſelf, becauſe the Medicine, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> here diſcours'd of, may be as much exceeded by Poſterity; a piece of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration and good nature, wanting in many of the Novel Writers; eſpecially <hi>Helmont,</hi> and all the little Chymiſts that pretend to be his followers, though they are ſo, in nothing ſo much, as in this ranting opprobrious way.</p>
            <p>Somewhat of example, and imitation I might alledg; and excuſe the preſumption, by the Mode of the undertaking, for ſuch the practice of this preſent Age hath made it, it being become frequent to examine, cenſure, and publickly reject, almoſt all the old re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived
<pb facs="tcp:106833:10"/>Opinions and Practices; and intro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce new ones, not only in Phyſick, but Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinity, Philoſophy, and all ſorts of Learning and Arts: this is the avowed deſign (and hath been very well performed by ſome) of thoſe learned Men: the Lord <hi>Bacon, des Cartes, Gaſſendus,</hi> Dr. <hi>Charleton,</hi> Mr. <hi>Hobs,</hi> Sir <hi>T. Brown,</hi> Dr. <hi>Mayow, Fr. Travaginus, Guardinus, Honoratus, Fabri,</hi> and many more <hi>Philoſophers:</hi> by <hi>Paracelſus, Helmont, Severinus, Hoſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manus, Zwelver, Crollius, Sylvius de Boe,</hi> the Author of <hi>Medela Medicinae,</hi> and all the <hi>Chymiſts;</hi> by Dr. <hi>Harvey,</hi> the <hi>Bartholines, Theod. Kirkringius, N. Steno, J. Swammerdam, M. Malpig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lius, Reg. de Graet,</hi> and all the Neoterick <hi>Anatomiſts:</hi> by Mr. <hi>R. Hook, Galile<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us,</hi> and the <hi>Copernicans,</hi> Mr. <hi>R. Boyle,</hi> Dr. <hi>Willis,</hi> Dr. <hi>Lower,</hi> Mr. <hi>Newton,</hi> Mr. <hi>Glanvil,</hi> &amp;c. with all the <hi>Virtuoſi,</hi> beſides the ſhoal of Yelpers after amendments, and Reformation, in matters relating to the Church and Religion. In fine, it's a liberty
<pb facs="tcp:106833:10"/>every one takes, as he (at leaſt) fancieth he hath reaſon on his ſide, to explode old opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions and practices, and introduce new ones; how much Reaſon, how many undoubted Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periments, and how many authentick Authors (the three grand inducements to believe) I have on mine, to juſtifie my deſign, and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lige my profeſsion, will without doubt appear effectually to all ingenious practiſers of it.</p>
            <p>And as in the Hiſtories of the lives of great Men, though they became renowned, by but one eminent act; all their leſſer performan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces are recorded (though no way contributing) to their fame; ſo I have given an account of the other many Vertues of <hi>Oleum Terebin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thinae,</hi> beſides that for which it is here prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipally celebrated, by which I hope I have made no unneceſſary or impertinent acceſſion, to the reputation of the Medicine, or price of the Book.</p>
            <p>And laſtly, I have ſuperadded, an account of a new way of Amputation, and a ſpeedier of healing the ſtumps by Conſolidation, which (how <hi>paradoxical</hi> ſoever it may ſeem) hath
<pb facs="tcp:106833:11"/>many advantages to the Practitioner and Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient, above all the yet knowu and practiſed ways; ſome other Curioſities are ready for the Publick, if thy candor and kindneſs to theſe invite them to forſake that privacy they enjoy, under his cuſtody, who is more kind to himſelf, than (without ſuch a temptation to allure, and encour agement to ſecure him) to hazard more than once, thy ſpleen or thy ſcorn.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>Plim. <date>July <hi>8. 1678.</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>J. Y.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:106833:11"/>
            <head>THE SUMMARY.</head>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE accidental occaſion of penning and pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhing this Letter. <hi>Page 1, 2</hi>
               </item>
               <item>An Abridgment of the moſt notorious incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veniencies and miſchiefs, reſulting from the commonly practiſed ways of ſtopping the bleeding of Wounds. <hi>p. 3</hi>
               </item>
               <item>No certain infallible Medicine, or Method yet found that can do it. <hi>p. 4.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The projected Method of the Diſcourſe; right ways of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraining the hemorrhagies of Wounds, firſt by cooling and ſtagnating the blood, and by what means it is uſual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally performed. <hi>p. 5</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Exploded as an Impediment to digeſtion; cold things perni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciouſly uſed to cure Wound-fevers, becauſe that accident is inevitable, and uſeful. <hi>p. 6</hi>
               </item>
               <item>This Method defective as to its main intention, hazarding Convulſions, Palſey's, After-fluxes. <hi>p. 7</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Catarrhs, a fatal inſtance thereof; why ſuch means are pertinent, and ſucceſsful in other ſanguinary fluxes, <hi>p. 8</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Periodical Hemoptyſis ſometimes healthful. <hi>p. 9</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The ſecond way by Eſcharoticks: what they are, Mercurial and Arſenical ones are miſchievous, proved in a notable inſtance. <hi>p. 10</hi>
               </item>
               <pb facs="tcp:106833:12"/>
               <item>Their venene and acid particles, hurt the Nerves, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> ſome preparations of both are benign. <hi>p. 11</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Sublimated Mercury uſually adulterate: the ill effects thereof in Mercurius Dulcis; directions how to diſcover it. <hi>p. 12</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Actual Cauteries, horrible, ſcandalous, cruel. <hi>p. 13</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Difficult, painful, fallible. <hi>p. 14</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The great benefit of them in other caſes. <hi>p. 15</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Corroſives hurt the Nerves by their acidity, and ſo beget direful ſymptomes. <hi>p. 16</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Fluxes breaks a new after the falling away of the Eſchar, begets a debilitating gleet, ill-ſhaped. <hi>p. 17</hi>
               </item>
               <item>And difficultly cured Stumps, Eſchars difficultly and dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerouſly removed, naſtily continued, and procraſtinates the cure. Third way is by coagulating the blood, in the mouths of the Veſſels, what Medicines effect it: they are often ineffectual, tedious, beget crudity, are naſty, ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times mortifie. <hi>p. 19</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The <hi>Aq. Styptica</hi> R. often ſucceſsleſs even in deſpicable Hemorrhagies. <hi>p. 20</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Buttons ſometimes harmful. <hi>p. 21</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Divers inconveniencies in the thumbing, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> A fourth way by clammy things choaking the Veſſels, is tedious, filthy, uncertain, hazards new Fluxes. <hi>p. 23</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Fifth way by ligation of the Veſſel, tedious, ſucceſsleſs, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cident to after-flux, and on ſome accounts impoſſible, it's uſe in other caſes. <hi>p. 24</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Sixth by Sarcoticks, what ſuch are, they are tedious, uncertain, filthy, perverts the courſe of Arts intention, <hi>Galen</hi>'s powder doth not ſo reſtrain Hemorrhagies, nor any other Medicine. <hi>p. 25</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Proved <hi>de facto,</hi> the ſeventh way by revulſion and deri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation: how performed. <hi>p. 26</hi>
               </item>
               <item>How by Cups they are inſignificant, how by Frictions. <hi>p. 27</hi>
               </item>
               <pb facs="tcp:106833:12"/>
               <item>Which are ineffectual and dangerous, how by Ligature. <hi>p. 28</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Their deſign rational, but not compleat; a Caution about them. <hi>p. 29</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A particular way of Ligature in Amputations recommend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, ſome cautions. <hi>p. 30</hi>
               </item>
               <item>How by Phlebotomy, very advantageous in other bleedings but in that of Wounds, is partial, needleſs, and often miſchievous. <hi>p. 31</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Hinders digeſtion, though in ſome extraordinary circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances it furthers it. <hi>p. 32</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The <hi>Germans</hi> reject phlebotomizing of wounded Men: it's improperly and precariouſly uſed to prevent Wound-fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers, which will occur in deſpight of monſtruous evacuation that way. <hi>p. 33</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Confirmed by obſervation, and illuſtrated by compariſon with the Small-pox. <hi>p. 34</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Wherein the Fever beginning them is proved inevitable, and ſooneſt cured by digeſtives and hot things: which Method is alſo beſt in Wounds till Coction be made, yet with caution. <hi>p. 35, 36</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The laſt way of ſtopping Hemorrhagies is by cloſing and uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the bleeding Veſſels, by ſtyptick agglutinators: it's not evident the <hi>Aqua Styptica</hi> ſo performs it. <hi>p. 37</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Another way mentioned by <hi>Pareus</hi> and Dr. <hi>Read,</hi> rejected: An Objection againſt the novelty of our Medicine. <hi>p. 38</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Anſwered, in that the old way wrought not the effects ſo well as ours: Many die of the loſs of blood not conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered, or known; the other Methods not always nor al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together fallible, though not comparable to this. <hi>p. 39</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Divers Phaenomena of Oil of <hi>Turpentine</hi> and humane blood. <hi>Exp. 1.</hi> It hardens and becometh a firm inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument. <hi>p. 40</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Exp. 2.</hi> Confirms the ſame when mixed with blood, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrated further by <hi>Exp. 3. p. 41</hi>
               </item>
               <pb facs="tcp:106833:13"/>
               <item>It coagulates even the ſerous part of the moſt ſerous blood, into a tough ſubſtance. <hi>p. 42</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Whitens the Surface thereof, and makes it very tough. <hi>p. 43</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Exp. 7.</hi> Blood ſo coagulated is a great Balſam for Wounds. <hi>p. 44</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Other Experiments recommended to trial for the further dilucidating this matter. <hi>p. 45</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Communicated Experiments ought to be tried more than once, if they fail. <hi>p. 46</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Oil of <hi>Turpentine</hi> mechanically proved to ſtay bleedings by contracting the ends of the Veſſels, coagulating the blood internally and externally, and ſo uniting them. <hi>p. 46, 47</hi>
               </item>
               <item>It's actual heat contributes, as doth (poſſibly) ſome ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtringing quality known to be in the Tree: directions for the choice and uſe of this Oil. <hi>p. 48</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Spirit and Oil, names promiſcuouſly given it, though it be properly an Oil, becauſe unctuous; ſome differences there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in. <hi>p. 49</hi>
               </item>
               <item>When the hotteſt is to be preferred. <hi>p. 50</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Medicine often adulterate, the Guaranty of the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thecaries Hall ſome encouragement for future confidence in Chymical Remedies. This muſt be uſed hot: the ways of preventing it from kindling, both at Sea and Land. <hi>p. 51, 52</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Ligature and Defenſatives muſt be uſed therewith: it uſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally doth its work at once, though ſome circumſtances may require its repetition. <hi>p. 53</hi>
               </item>
               <item>It may be applyed any where ſave near the Eye, and the Breaſt if an Inſlammation be concomitant. <hi>p. 54</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Otherwiſe is very proper, being pectoral, pulmonick, proved from good Authors; how to be uſed to ſtumps of the Thigh, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Stabs. <hi>p. 55</hi>
               </item>
               <pb facs="tcp:106833:13"/>
               <item>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſed to a hot, or to a cholerick habit, it veſicates, but in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocently. <hi>p. 56</hi>
               </item>
               <item>When the oldeſt Oil is to be preferred. <hi>p. 57</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The other Vertues thereof with reſpect to Wounds: It ſtops the <hi>Synovia,</hi> the advantages thereby acrewed, it's the beſt curer of punctured Nerves. <hi>p. 58, 59</hi>
               </item>
               <item>It excellently digeſts, without the attraction other applica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of that nature make, the benefit thereof: An Obje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction. <hi>p. 60</hi>
               </item>
               <item>How the Medicine can reſtrain Hemorrhagies, and yet di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſteth. <hi>p. 61</hi>
               </item>
               <item>It's the beſt Balm for wounded Nerves, no Wound can be made without hurting their Genus. <hi>p. 62</hi>
               </item>
               <item>It contracts Wounds, prevents their expanſion, without the inconveniency of other applications: It healeth Punctures and inciſed Wounds, by ſympathy: An Objection about the incongruity of a digeſtive and conſolidative quality, anſwered: the Magnetick <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nguent, and ſympathetick Powder miſtaken: how Conſolidatives cure. <hi>p. 64</hi>
               </item>
               <item>This Medicine effects thoſe ends, without the ſymptomes at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending the other Methods. <hi>p. 65</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The pertinency of confirming Theories by Experiments and obſervations: divers Obſervations proving the Vertue of <hi>Ol. Terebinthinae</hi> to reſtrain Hemorrhagies: Obſ. <hi>1.</hi> in an amputation of the Arm. <hi>p. 66</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Another of a ſphacelated Leg, on an aged extenuate Man. <hi>p. 67, 68</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Two the like obſervations. <hi>p. 70</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Obſ. <hi>3.</hi> An Hemorrhage in a ſinuous <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>lcer from an Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tery in the Cheek: another of the ſame. <hi>p. 71, 72</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Obſ. <hi>5.</hi> A Wound in the Thigh. <hi>p. 73</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Obſ. <hi>7.</hi> Thorow the Body, and down the Throat. <hi>p. 74</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Obſ. <hi>8.</hi> From a Cancered Breaſt. <hi>p. 75</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Obſ. <hi>9.</hi> From a Wound by Caſtration. <hi>p. 76, 77</hi>
               </item>
               <pb facs="tcp:106833:14"/>
               <item>A punctured Artery in the Hand, and inciſed Wound in the Metatarſus. <hi>p. 78</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Another Amputation of the Leg. <hi>p. 79</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A Wound on the Forehead, which bled impetuouſly ten days after the firſt Dreſs: ſome painful ſymptomes fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing the application of our Medicine, and their cauſes. <hi>p. 81, 82</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Crurals wounded, and cured by our Medicine. <hi>p. 83</hi>
               </item>
               <item>An Objection anſwered. <hi>p. 84</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The many other Vertues of <hi>Ol. Terebinthinae</hi> externally applied, frim <hi>page 84,</hi> to <hi>page 87.</hi> The Vertues there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of internally adminiſtred, from <hi>page 84,</hi> to <hi>page 89.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Authors whence collected. <hi>p. 90</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Concluſion. <hi>p. 91</hi>
               </item>
               <item>An inſtance in Mr. <hi>Wiſeman</hi>'s Book that ſeems to op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, anſwered. <hi>p. 91</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Medicines curing the punctures of Nerves or Tendons ought to be hot, dry, and of ſubtil parts, proved by many Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors. <hi>p. 93</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Accidents attending bleeding, ill habits, attributed to Punctures or Tendons without juſt cauſe: ſome inſtances thereof. <hi>p. 93, 94, 95, 96, 97</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Hiſtory of a very remarkable punctured Tendon in a Woman. <hi>p. 98, 99, 100, 101, 102, 103, 104</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A penetrating Wound of the left Ilia, with the Hemor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rhage of an Artery wounded thereby, reſtrained and cured by this Medicine, not very hot. <hi>105, 106, 107</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Amputated Stumps way be cicatrized without ſcaling the bone, but not without hazard. <hi>p. 108, 109</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Bones may be bare without fouling: all foul ones muſt be ſcaled. <hi>p. 110</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The manner of amputating a Member, ſo as to cure it by Conſolidation. <hi>p. 111</hi>
               </item>
               <pb facs="tcp:106833:14"/>
               <item>Some Circumſtances to be obſerved in this new Method. <hi>p. 112</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Conſolidation of fleſh never before united, is no Novelty: divers inſtances thereof. <hi>p. 113</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Some particular caſes where this ſort of Amputation can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be uſed: the advantages this way hath above that commonly practiſed, in that it's cured more ſpeedy, without leaving a dyſepulotick <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>lcer, or ſcaling the Bone. <hi>p. 114</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Or expenſive profluence of blood, <hi>&amp;c. p. 115</hi>
               </item>
               <item>How fleſh may be ſuppoſed to ſtop the Hemorrhagies of wounded Veſſels. <hi>p. 116, 117, 118</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Cure this way is done with leſs pain; and why, eaſier and cheaper to the Chirurgeon, more firmly, not apt to break up, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and more capable of uſing an Artificial Leg. <hi>p. 119, 120.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <pb facs="tcp:106833:15"/>
            <head>The Reader will injure himſelf, and prejudice the Author, if he adventure to peruſe this Diſcourſe, till he have corrected with his Pen the following Errata; which by reaſon of the Author's abſence from the Preſs, have occurred.</head>
            <p>PAge 1. line 3. <hi>read</hi> Vertues, p. 5. l. 22. <hi>r.</hi> eight diſtinctions, p. 6. l. 4. put an <hi>aſterisk</hi> over <hi>Hippocrates,</hi> and another in the oppoſite Margent over, <hi>in hypp. praed.</hi> p. 7. l. 14. <hi>r.</hi> injured, p. 9. in the Margent, <hi>r. anno</hi> 73: p. 11. l. 27. leave out of, p. 15. l. 16. <hi>r.</hi> theſe diſſuading, p. 17. l. 13. <hi>r.</hi> mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruous, p. 20. l. 8. <hi>r.</hi> Styptick liquor, p. 26. l. 9. <hi>r.</hi> incarnative, p. 30. l. 8. <hi>r.</hi> to lay a wadd, l. 18. <hi>r.</hi> Veſſels, p. 32. l. 1. <hi>r.</hi> uſed to, p. 35. put an <hi>aſterisk</hi> on the quotation from Dr. <hi>Willis,</hi> l. 13. <hi>r.</hi> Phlegmon: in the margent <hi>r. dixit,</hi> p. 36. l. 30. <hi>r.</hi> digeſtives, p. 40. l. 22. <hi>r.</hi> for what, p. 41. l. 26. it adhereth, p. 43. l. 7. leave out, that, l. 13. <hi>r.</hi> it to be, p. 44. l. 23. leave out, yet, p. 52. l. 21. <hi>r.</hi> their diſcharge, p. 54. l. 2. <hi>r.</hi> inſinuating, p. 57. l. 6. any others, l. 21. the firſt ſentence in the laſt period, ſhould be joined to the preceding, p. 58. l. 2. <hi>r.</hi> general, l. 24. <hi>r.</hi> nervous liquor, p. 63. l. 21. <hi>r.</hi> page 23. p. 64. l. 2. that I attribute, in the Margent, <hi>r.</hi> tract 1. p. 67. l. 4. <hi>r.</hi> Veſſels, p. 78. l. 8. <hi>r. Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pus,</hi> p. 80. l. 16. <hi>r.</hi> two, p. 82. l. 2. <hi>r. Margarit,</hi> l. 20. <hi>r.</hi> temporal and frontal, p. 87. l. 21. <hi>r. Nervinum,</hi> p. 88. l. 18. <hi>r.</hi> Comphory, p. 93. l. 4. <hi>r.</hi> lib. 6. melſ. p. 94. l. 1. <hi>r.</hi> Phlebotomy there, being ſuch, p. 102. l. 2. <hi>r. Coag.</hi> p. 104. l. 15. leave out q. ſ. p. 105. l. 6. <hi>r.</hi> worſe, p. 111. l. 9. <hi>r.</hi> the uſual, p. 115. l. 6. <hi>r. Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſarcoſis,</hi> p. 118. l. 5. leave out, no. Some miſ-pointings and ſuch leſs ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vious Errata, are left to the Readers Ingenuity to correct as he finds them.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:106833:15"/>
            <head>AN EPISTOLARY DISCOURSE, Concerning the Virtue of <hi>Oleum Terebinthinae.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Can not forget, that at one of the many times, I had the happineſs to be <hi>(Worthy Sir)</hi> in your company in <hi>London,</hi> ſome other of the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culty being preſent, there occurred a Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe concerning <hi>Reſtringent Medicins:</hi> by which was meant, ſuch as are the moſt cele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brated, approved, and practiſed, to reſtrain the <hi>Homorrhagies</hi> of Wounds; the <hi>Aqua Styp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tica,</hi> and <hi>Galen</hi>'s famous Powder, together with proper <hi>Ligature,</hi> were preferred to all others. After ſome diſcourſe on this occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, I preſumed to offer one, which (beſides its other very many advantages for curing Wounds) I had found by many trials, the moſt happy and ſucceſsful, I had ever read, heard off, or experimented, and that was common <hi>Oleum Terebinthinae:</hi> Mr. H— making ſome doubt concerning it, conſtrained me,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:106833:16"/>though before ſuch intuitive men, to attempt the reaſon thereof; it being indecent to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe on Company, things which publick ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience had not avowed, or my ſelf could not as readily confirm by Senſe, or Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, as affirm by Narrative; it being more mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt where things ſeem improbable (though true) and not readily verifiable by reaſon, or experience, to be ſilent.</p>
            <p>Wherefore, becauſe the circumſtances al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed not of preſent proof, by the infallible teſt of the former, I offered by way of the latter, what my barren fancy could ſuggeſt to me under ſuch diſcouraging circumſtances, as were the ſudaineſs of the occaſion, my un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preparedneſs, and the ſagacity of the Compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, which could not but awe a more reſolute undertaker than my ſelf. What I offered, you ſeemed particularly pleaſed with, and adviſed me to make it known to the Publikk.</p>
            <p>Nothing ſo much as your approbation, could have perſuaded me to think ſo well of any thing I there ſuggeſted, nor ought be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides your Commands, have induced me to commit to every man's knowledge, what hath hitherto lain private in the breaſts of a very few; but Sir, your Judgment ought to be the touchſtone of my Reaſon, no leſs than your Commands, the unlocker of my greateſt and more ſecret <hi>Arcanum,</hi> whence the Patient,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:106833:16"/>and Practitioner, if any advantage accrew to either by this publication, become obliged and redevable to you; the defects, and miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carriages of what kind ſoever, ought only to reſt on my account.</p>
            <p>I know it's too common with many of the Fraternity, to ſlight and contemn all Novel diſcoveries, of this or the like nature, think<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that nothing can more effectually ſecure the bleeding of wounds, than Cauteries, Deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation, or what other ways Education or Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtom hath made more familiar and practicable to them, but all thoſe men do not conſider the direful conſequences of ſome; the unſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſsfulneſs of other ſuch means, and methods. The intolerable pain of Cauteries, whether actual or potential, are ſufficiently, and with good reaſon inveighed againſt, by <hi>Pareus, Wurts, &amp;c.</hi> The After-fluxes, notwithſtanding tying up the Veſſels, <hi>the Crudity and indigeſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on occaſioned by the common Stypticks, and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtringents, the Fevers, Mortifications, Convul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, loſs of ſubſtance, ill-ſhaped Cicatrices, and ſtumps, the tedious continuation of Eſchars, the the large, and enervating Synovia's;</hi> together with a number of other leſs accidents, that are the common and fatal conſequences of the u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſual and moſt practiſed ways, cannot poſſibly occur by the uſe of this Balſam, if the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rections herewith given be obſerved.</p>
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:106833:17"/>
            <p>Nor is the ſecuring <hi>Hemorrhagies</hi> ſo very trite and eaſie, as ſome men make it. You, Sir, do well know the contrary; and that the death of many a ſtout Souldier and hardy Seaman, too ſadly demonſtrates, that an infal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lible remedy, to ſtaunch the bleeding of Wounds is yet wanting, eſpecially ſuch an one, as with eaſe and benignity doth atchieve it; that this which I here recommend (though I affirm not its infallibility) merits the prece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dency of all yet known, and conſequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ought to have the eſteem of every Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſt, will I hope appear from the following Reaſons and Obſervations, the latter of which every ingenious Profeſſor may confirm and improve, as he hath occaſion and oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity.</p>
            <p>Give me leave, Sir, (after I have begged pardon for the preſumption of this Addreſs, to which I became inclined and encouraged, by your favourable thoughts of the more imperfect account I gave thereof, and on conſideration of the fitneſs ſuch diſcoveries have for your approbation and notice, as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing deſervedly the general ſuperintendent of thoſe for whom it's deſigned, and conſequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the moſt pertinent and proper hand, by which it could be conveyed to their know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, or recommended to their practice and conſideration) to manage my deſign, and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:106833:17"/>in this order and method. <hi>Firſt,</hi> To relate the ſeveral operations, methods, and medicaments, which are moſt uſually practiſed to ſtop or reſtrain <hi>Hemorrhagies,</hi> and therein to take occaſion to reflect on ſome, the moſt inartificial and ſucceſsleſs, and to reject them. <hi>Secondly,</hi> To endeavour to demonſtrate, how our Oil of Turpentine doth perform it. <hi>Third<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,</hi> To give ſome directions to be obſerved in the uſe, choice, and application thereof. <hi>Fourthly,</hi> To demonſtrate the other adventi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious benefits, acquired to Wounds, (beſides reſtraining the bleeding) by means of this Balſam. <hi>Fifthly,</hi> To illuſtrate, and confirm the truth of all <hi>de facto,</hi> by relating ſeveral obſervations, wherein it proved ſucceſsful. And <hi>laſtly,</hi> to relate the very many other me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicinal Vertues of this Oil, both as internal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly adminiſtred, or externally applied.</p>
            <p>The ways in general, by which the <hi>Hemor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rhagies</hi> of Veins and Arteries are ſtopped, are reducible to theſe ſeveral right diſtinctions.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The firſt, is by ſtagnating the blood in the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tream parts, and allaying its briskneſs, and mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in the larger Veſſels:</hi> which is atchieved by immerſing the body in cold water, or wrapping it in ſheets moiſt with <hi>Poſca,</hi> or adminiſtring Opiat medicines, or other ſuch whoſe cold quality fixeth the bloud, or ſlac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kens its circulation. Such are <hi>Sal Prunella, aq.
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:106833:18"/>Sperm. Ranarum,</hi> &amp;c. againſt all which I have this to Object.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> That it's a great retarder of digeſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; for whatever cooleth and allayeth fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentation, hinders maturation; this I ſpeak of it, when uſed to that degree it ought, to effect the aforeſaid deſign; not that I would wholly, even in the moſt ſedate temper omit the uſe of moderate Julaps, or ſometimes a ſlight <hi>Hypnotick,</hi> to aſſwage pain and procure reſt; nor on the other hand would I uſe them too liberally, as they frequently are, and that becauſe (as I have ſaid) they are ſo great an Impediment, to the ground-work of healing large Wounds, nor do I only diſlike their uſe where they pretend to ſtop Fluxes; but as commonly they are deſigned alſo, to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent and cure the ſymptomatical Fevers, u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſually attending green Wounds; for that Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver is not only neceſſary, but inevitable, and that becauſe it's uſually both the effect, and (pardon the <hi>Soleciſm</hi>) the cauſe alſo of di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſtion, as hath been long ſince intimated to us by <hi>Hipocrates,</hi> and<note n="*" place="margin">Lib. 47. cap. 2. <hi>in Hipp. prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dict.</hi> l. 1. c. 13.</note> 
               <hi>Galen.</hi> Therefore, where vehement ſymptoms make ſuch Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cines neceſſary, I would recommend the mix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of ſuch ingredients as may alſo promote the Coction, by which the Fever ſhall be more allayed, than by the cold, anodyne things: This in Julaps, is eaſily done by cocting in
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:106833:18"/>them, <hi>ſaffron, figs,</hi> &amp;c. or the good old Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſan-drink, of <hi>Hordeum</hi> and <hi>Liquoris.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> This way is defective, imperfect, fallible, and of it ſelf unable to anſwer the deſigned intention, or at beſt but a cojuvant Remedy, only quieting the motion of the bloud, while more ſecure ways of ſtopping the mouths of the Veſſels, may be made uſe of, compleatly to effect it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> By the uſe of Medicines highly cold, (whether actually, or potentially ſo) without which this deſign pretends not to be effected; the <hi>nervous genus,</hi> may become in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſured, whereby the common attendants of large Wounds, <hi>Palſie, Convulſion, Spaſms, Num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medneſs,</hi> and <hi>Inſenſation,</hi> may be occaſioned.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fourthly,</hi> The immerſing the Body in cold water, or the incloſing it in Linnen wet with Water and Vinegar; whatever advantage they may procure <hi>pro tempore,</hi> their after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>effects, are like to be very miſchievous; and contrary to the deſign of their uſe; and that is, provoking an after-flux, either by begetting heats, or a feveriſh motion in the bloud, which it accendeth as other colds do; that is, (to ſay nothing of the doctrine of <hi>Antiperiſtaſis</hi>) by ſhutting the pores of the skin, whereby the various recrements that uſed to tranſpire that way, being pent up, regurgitate, which Nature endeavouring
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:106833:19"/>to ſeparate, and reject by a febrile fermen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation; the bloud becomes inflamed; as is e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vident in <hi>Agues,</hi> the great heat in the hands, and feet, and toes, and fingers, and often <hi>Phlegmons</hi> (for ſuch are Kibes and Chilblains,) on them both, after great cold, and handling Snow: or by ſeparating the ſerous parts thereof; and ſo a<note n="*" place="margin">D. Low<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er de orig. Catarrh.</note> 
               <hi>Catarrh, Cough,</hi> &amp;c. is occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſioned, which begets ſuch a ſaltation in the bloud, that except the wounded Veſſels be well ſecured, it will very aptly break bounds: this is manifeſt in <hi>Phlebotomy,</hi> where it's fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent to put the Patient a Coughing, to make him bleed. I once had a near Relation, who to ſtop an <hi>Hemorrhage,</hi> lapped his naked body in moiſtned Sheets, but it begat a fatal <hi>Metap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toſis,</hi> or commutation, for ſuch a Catarrh en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſued, as dwindled away his life by a five months Conſumption: wherefore even in <hi>Hemoptyſis,</hi> or ſpitting of bloud, from the <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naſtomoſis</hi> of a Veſſel, either in the <hi>lungs, ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mach, ſpleen,</hi> &amp;c. It muſt be of hazardous uſe, in which caſes, though perhaps Opiats, and other coolers and thickeners may have been ſucceſsful; yet doth it not invalidate my objections againſt their uſe in bleeding of Wounds: becauſe <hi>firſt,</hi> no digeſtion being required in internal bleedings, as there is in Wounds, one great Objection againſt it, is unconcerned. <hi>Secondly,</hi> Internal bleedings
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:106833:19"/>are incapable of local applications, ſo that of neceſſity thoſe muſt be uſed, for being the leſs miſchievous, become the moſt conveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent. <hi>Thirdly,</hi> Internal bleedings are not ſo apt to be accompanied with <hi>Convulſions, Pal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies,</hi> &amp;c. as are Wounds and lacerations of the nervous parts, whereby another great in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conveniency in their uſe is taken away. <hi>Fourthly,</hi> Internal bleedings frequently pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed from <hi>redundancy, thinneſs, ſharpneſs, heat, fermentation,</hi> or the like ill temper of the bloud, by which it breaks through ſome of the ſmaller Veſſels (and that ſometimes with innocence and great advantage, as<note n="*" place="margin">Acta med. &amp; philoſ. Hafnienſia <hi>num. 73.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Bartholine</hi> inſtanceth, and <hi>Theod.</hi>
               <note n="†" place="margin">Spicileg. Anatom.</note> 
               <hi>Kirkringius</hi> in a Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riodical <hi>Hemoptyſis,</hi> as harmleſs, and healthy, as thoſe lunary diſcharges from Women,) to ſecure which, there needs no more but to empty them by <hi>Phlebotomy,</hi> or cool, thicken, and ſweeten the bloud, as the cauſe may re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire. <hi>Laſtly,</hi> It's very rare and unuſual for internal bleedings, proceeding from, or cauſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by the wounding, <hi>Rupture, Eroſion, Diape<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſis,</hi> &amp;c. of a Vein or Artery, though but a ſmall one, to be cured by any means whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever, and that becauſe they admit not of lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal application, the moſt certain, if not the only way by which they can be cured.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The ſecond general way of ſtopping fluxes of bloud, is by inducing an Eſchar, or Cruſt, by
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:106833:20"/>which the bleeding mouth of the Veſſel is choked;</hi> theſe are procured either by actual or poten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial <hi>Cauteries:</hi> the manner of performing the former, is too trite and vulgar to deſcribe, the latter is the effect of <hi>Eſcarotical</hi> applicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons: ſuch are <hi>Vitriolum uſtum, Mercurius ſublimatus corroſivus, Arſenicum, Oleum Vitrio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>li, Calcanthum, Calx Viva, Aq. fortis, Aq. Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gis,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Before I remark on them, in their general qualifications as <hi>Corroſives,</hi> I ſhall make ſome reflections on thoſe that are <hi>Mercurially</hi> and <hi>Arſenically</hi> ſuch: I find divers Authors re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commend them,<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pet. Fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt. ob. chyr.</hi> lib. 6. <hi>I. Vigo.</hi> lib. 3. tr. 1. c. 3. <hi>Clow's.</hi> page 135. <hi>A. Pareus.</hi> lib. 9. c. 7. M. <hi>Wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man.</hi> lib. 5. c. 2.</note> and have heard of ſome Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctitioners that continue their uſe in this caſe, but with mortal Effects, as moſt notoriouſly appeared, <hi>Anno</hi> 1666. at which time, nine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teen amputated men were ſent to <hi>Harwich,</hi> out of one of the Capital Ships, and at the ſame time and place the like number from another; of the one died all, except one, and of the other all were cured, ſave that ſmall number; this account I had from a very credible Artiſt, then in the Fleet: where it was generally underſtood, that the <hi>Mercu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rial</hi> applications had made the one ſo unhap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py, and the contrary the other ſo fortunate; without doubt, that great diſparity in their fates was occaſioned by the venomous par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles of the <hi>Mercury</hi> inſinuated to the Veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:106833:20"/>or from its conſtant and vehement corro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of the Nerves: to which <hi>Mercury</hi> as ſuch, and more ſo, as acid, is a known E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemy.</p>
            <p>Its true, that <hi>precipitated Mercury</hi> and ſome <hi>mercurial</hi> waters, prepared with <hi>Sublimate,</hi> are of ſingular good uſe in Ulcers: the former being of ancient practice, and at this day uſed as an excellent <hi>digeſtive</hi> and <hi>mundifier</hi> of ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>did Ulcers: but the preparations of them both, doth either ſo explode their mortal and venenoſe Particles, as in the former, or dilute them as in the latter, that they cannot have thoſe poiſonous effects.</p>
            <p>It is evident alſo to the reaſon of every man, that when Mercurial preparations are applied to the newly divided ends of thoſe ſenſible parts, they more aptly inſinuate their malignity, invenome their Liquors, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce thoſe other fatal effects mentioned, by the intolerable pain they beget, being applied to parts of ſuch exquiſite ſenſe, even when that faculty is irritated and become exaſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate by their <hi>contuſion, laceration, divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>The poiſonous quality in <hi>Sublimate,</hi> (which was the Medicine of the above intimated Gentleman, applied to his ſtumps to ſtay the <hi>Hemorrhage</hi>) may be inconſiderable, if rightly prepared, but its corroſive ſalts are unmo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vable,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:106833:21"/>a ſort of it uſually brought from a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad, and what is ſometimes made in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> being done with <hi>Arſenick</hi> is very mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal, as <hi>Monſ.</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">P. 2. l. 2. c. 10. ſect. 4. <hi>&amp; Barth. in Beguin.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Le Febure</hi> complains; though there are<note n="†" place="margin">
                  <hi>F. Wurtts</hi> p. 4. c. 6.</note> preparations of <hi>Arſenick</hi> it ſelf, which are ſafe enough and with eaſe ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied, even to ſo tender a part as the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rethra,</hi> as<note n="c" place="margin">
                  <hi>De uti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lit. Philoſ. Nat.</hi> part 2. Eſs. 5. cap. 8.</note> 
               <hi>Mr. Boyle</hi> tells us, in a notable inſtance. Now becauſe a great deal of miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chief hath been often done by ill-prepared <hi>Sublimate,</hi> not only in the preſent caſes we are diſcourſing of, but when internally given, as in <hi>Mercurius dulcis</hi> which is prepared of it, and crude <hi>Mercury</hi> [<hi>the fatal effects of which are now cruciating an unhappy</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">The on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Son of Sir <hi>H. P.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi> I am attending on, who receiving but ſix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teen grains thereof in a purgative <hi>Bolus,</hi> hath for many days, endured ſevere tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, and is now languiſhing beyond hope of recovery.] I will communicate to my Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the young Chirurgion a few directions, by which he ſhall diſcover whether it be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared with <hi>Arſenick,</hi> or not.</p>
            <p>℞ <hi>Mercury ſublimated</hi> ℈j. powder it, and throw thereon a little <hi>oleum Tartari per de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liquium;</hi> If it give the Oil a blue tincture, it's prepared with <hi>Arſenick,</hi> and is dangerous; but if it give the Oil a purple tincture, it is good and ſafe.</p>
            <p>℞ <hi>Sublimated Mercury</hi> Mairſs. powder it, and
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:106833:21"/>lay it in a Silver ſpoon, hold it over a fire till it evaporate; if it leave a Purple ſpot, it's good: if any other colour, its dangerous.</p>
            <p>It diſcovers it ſelf alſo by the ſtrong <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenical</hi> ſmell, and by cleaving to your fingers: ſaith <hi>M. Le Febure ubi ſupra.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To proceed, <hi>Cauteries and Cauſticks,</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered only as they corrode, have too fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently the ill effects, hereafter to be mentio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, which though evident to every mans ſenſe, and complained by good<note n="*" place="margin">A. <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rey.</hi> l. 9. c. 7. <hi>&amp; in</hi> lib. 20. <hi>F. Wurts</hi> p. 1. c. 4. part 4. c. 56.</note> 
               <hi>Authors,</hi> have notwithſtanding been continued with ſtrange fondneſs by many, who think they can never ſecure an <hi>Hemorrhage</hi> without them.</p>
            <p>As to <hi>actual Cauteries</hi> uſed in the caſe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore us, beſides the miſchiefs they occaſion, and that are common to them as <hi>Eſcharoticks,</hi> they have their ſpecial ones, of begetting great dread and horrour in the Patient, and no leſs ſcandal to the Art and <hi>Artiſts,</hi> as is evident in the common upbraidings on that occaſion, to be found in ſuch as <hi>Quevedo,</hi> and the more ſolemnly cruel reſentments of mankind againſt them, in the fate of <hi>Archa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gathos.</hi> Were there not milder ways of at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining the ſame ends, or were this infal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lible, it were ſome juſtification and excuſe; but the contrary to both being evident, our cruelty is beyond all Apology: when a member after it hath been lacerated, and
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:106833:22"/>torn aſunder by a Canon ſhot, and under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gone a new extirpation by the <hi>Chyrurgeons</hi> Knife and Saw, muſt be cruciated by the dreadful, often needleſs, frequently miſchie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vous application of his hot Irons alſo, ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gueth us to have Lions paws as well as hearts: as if becauſe an old ſaying had given us the one, we would of our ſelves aſſume the other.</p>
            <p>It's moreover an operation of great nicity and difficult performance, eſpecially in the hurry of Sea-fight; for if the Iron be too hot, it either brings off the <hi>Eſchar</hi> with it, or leaves it looſe; if not hot enough, it begets nothing but pain and anguiſh; theſe impeachments are ſo plain, that every one will excuſe my Cenſure. I leave it to the conſideration of any ingenious Men, to i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>magine how difficult it is to heat thoſe dread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Inſtruments to that exact degree they ought: and how dangerous when it's time to uſe them, to delay till they are reduced to it.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Summary</hi> is this; That conſidering this operation to be always terrible and painful; ſometimes needleſs, frequently miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chievous, ever difficult to be done Artifici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally and exactly, often<note n="*" place="margin">S. For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mius, Ob. <hi>1.</hi>
               </note> ſucceſsleſs, beſides the other Objections to which its liable, in common with Corroſives; and that means
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:106833:22"/>more ſucceſsful, more facilly performed, ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noxious to none of the ill conſequences hereby, are to be had; (all which are evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent,) it ought to be exploded by every one that valueth either his own reputation, that of his Art, or the good of his Patient.</p>
            <p>I detract not hereby from the due worth of ſuch Operations when uſed to their proper ends and occaſions. I deſign only to ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt the impertinence thereof in the parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular caſe before us, and to dehort my Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the young Practitioner from being for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward with them, in recent Wounds, Ampu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations, &amp;c. the incomparable good effects of their application in other caſes, where their diſſuading circumſtances do not exiſt, is known to your ſelf, Sir, and all good Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſts; and is well recounted by <hi>Johannes de Vigo,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Lib. 8. cap. 15.</note> more principally after the extirpation of a <hi>Cancer,</hi> or a mortified part, where there is reaſon to doubt that ſome remains are behind, of either the malignant matter, or cadaverous fleſh, as alſo in all venomous Wounds; but in all theſe, their uſe is not to reſtrain the bleeding, but to extinguiſh the poiſon and quicken the ſenſe and life of the part, which it incomparably doth.</p>
            <p>Having in this <hi>Claſſis</hi> conſidered, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected all actual Cauteries, and thoſe potenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al ones that are ſo, by any Mercurial or Arſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nical
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:106833:23"/>mixture: I come to examine thoſe which in a general ſenſe are ſo denomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, not having any venom in them, againſt the application of which to green Wounds, for ſtopping fluxes of bloud, by inducing an an <hi>Eſchar,</hi> I have theſe following Obje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> It's a received truth, and of gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral belief in <hi>Phyſick, that all Acids are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jurious to the Nerves.</hi> It's ſpoken of them as received internally. If ſo, after they are <hi>diluted</hi> by the vehicle wherein they are ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtred, and the Juices they circulate in, how much more ſo ſhall ſuch potent ones be, when ſolely applied to them, when their tenderneſs and ſenſe is irritated by wound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, &amp;c. Now all Corroſives being ſo from their acid Salts: they when applied to a Wound, (ſuppoſe it the ſtump of a mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber) although with the utmoſt care, dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence and skill of the applier, confined to the mouths of the bleeding Veſſels, ſhall in deſpight of all his endeavours to prevent it, diffuſe ſo, that the ends of the Nerves, the <hi>Perioſteum,</hi> and all the ſenſible parts ſhall ſuffer by their teeth, the effects of which will be <hi>Pain, Convulſion, Watching, Fever, Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>novia,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> It often happeneth, that when the <hi>Eſchar</hi> they beget falleth away, the <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morrhage</hi>
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:106833:23"/>reneweth, and is then with much more difficulty reſtrained. Proofs hereof were endleſs and needleſs.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> Though a <hi>Cautery</hi> or <hi>Cauſtick</hi> may happily ſtop bleeding, it occaſions a flux not much leſs miſchievous than that of the Veins and Arteries, to wit a large<note n="*" place="margin">The meaning of the word, and the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverfie of the thing, is at large in D. <hi>Sennert. de chymic. cum Ariſt. &amp; Gal. conſenſu ac diſſenſu.</hi> c. 15.</note> 
               <hi>Synovia,</hi> or weeping of the other Veſſels, which ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver occurreth near the degree where thoſe ſharp applications are not made. Sometimes I have ſeen it flow at that extravagant rate, as in a very few hours to wet the whole bandage: the menſtruous expence of which <hi>Serum</hi> (whether it be that of the bloud, <hi>Lymphaducts,</hi> or <hi>Nerves,</hi> or all) muſt conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derably dry, enervate and diſpirit. If their uſes in the body, (according to <hi>Severinus, Paracelſus, Gliſſon,</hi> and <hi>Scheunemannus</hi>) are to humect, ſtrengthen, convey the animal Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits, and (as <hi>Dr. Gliſſon</hi> particularly of the <hi>Succus Nervoſum</hi>) to nouriſh.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fourthly,</hi> It often happeneth, where ſtrong <hi>Eſcaroticks</hi> have been applied, that when the Cruſt hath been removed, ſo much of the fleſh is found eroded and come away there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by, the remaining ſound part alſo ſhrunk ſo far back, (as they moſt evidently do after <hi>Cauteries</hi>) that the bone is left bare, and ſtands out beyond the Level: ſo that the Chirurgeon muſt either take it off anew, (a
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:106833:24"/>thing not eaſie to be done well) or by te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dious incarnation, raiſe the fleſh to it, the conſequences of which will be an incura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble <hi>dyſepulotick</hi> Ulcer, which alſo depri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth the Patient of benefit by that part of our Art, which teacheth us to ſupply the defects of Nature, it being difficult, if not impoſſible for him, to uſe an artificial ſtump or ſupplemental Leg, till the Ulcer be <hi>ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>catrized.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fifthly,</hi> The difficulty and danger of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moving <hi>Eſcars,</hi> the tediouſneſs thereof, the filthy ſtench and putrefaction thereby occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſioned, are ills that are particular to this way of ſtopping the <hi>hemorrhage</hi> of a Wound.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The third way of reſtraining fluxes of blood from wounded Veins or Arteries, is by coagu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lating it in or about the mouths of the Veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels bleeding, whereby they are choaked;</hi> this is acquired either by local Medicines, or ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nual Operation: the former is done by all ſweet vitriolate Medicines,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>G. Hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtins.</hi> ob. 12. l. 9. telleth us, of the <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morrhage</hi> of an Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tery ſtay'd by laying a bit of <hi>O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pium</hi> in the place bleeding.</note> ſuch as the <hi>Aq. ſtyptica</hi> R. &amp;c. as alſo by <hi>Narcoticks</hi> and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Specificks: ſuch are <hi>Pulv. Bufonum, Bufo Siccata, Lapis haematitis, Bole,</hi> &amp;c. and the common applications of that nature, but they are not ſeldom ineffectual, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther becauſe the Veſſels are large, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently the torrent of the blood alſo, which admits not of the deſigned effect on
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:106833:24"/>them, either by diluting the application, or waſhing it off, and the ſmall coagulations it may induce before they become large, or firm enough to anſwer the intention; or elſe from the <hi>craſis</hi> of the blood it ſelf, which in many habits is ſo <hi>ſerous,</hi> hot and thin as renders it incapable of coagulation by ſuch weak cauſes: neither of theſe are poſſible when our Medicine is applyed. For <hi>firſt</hi> its being <hi>unctuous,</hi> will not admit its mix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture with bloud, wherefore it cannot be di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luted thereby. <hi>Secondly,</hi> It's evident by experiment the fourth following, that it thickens even the <hi>ſerum</hi> of the bloud, and therefore cannot fail of coagulating it, though the temperament thereof be very ſerous.</p>
            <p>Every Artiſt uſing this Method, is ſo ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſive of the uncertainty of it's effects,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>S. Formi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us,</hi> contin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued ſuch a dreſſing 7 days with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out mov<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them. <hi>Obſerv.</hi> 1. to ſtay the <hi>hemorrhage</hi> of a bleed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Axil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lary,</hi> after Cautery, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> had been in vain uſed.</note> (eſpecially when large Veſſels are wound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed) that they fear to looſe or remove ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Ligature, or dreſs, until the ſecond or third, (ſometimes not until the fourth) day, although it be lacerated Wound, whereby great putrefaction is ingendred, cauſing faint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, mortification of the part, or at beſt crudity and indigeſtion by extinguiſhing the natural heat, and deſtroying the <hi>Craſis</hi> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of; not to mention the ſtench and ſcanda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous noiſom ſmell it uſually yieldeth by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:106833:25"/>of the putrilage, nor the pain of the Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gature ſo long continued to retain the dreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings; nor its contributing to a <hi>Gangrene</hi> or the like ills by its continual preſſure, whereby the influx of the Spirits are im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peded.</p>
            <p>The great noiſe and fame of the <hi>Royal Styptick figure</hi> invented by <hi>Monſieur Denys,</hi> communicated to his <hi>Majeſty,</hi> approved and<note n="*" place="margin">Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoph. Tranſ. <hi>n. 94, 95, 96.</hi>
               </note> tryed by <hi>Mr. Serjeant Wiſeman</hi> and others: of which <hi>Mr. Oldenburgh</hi> gives us a large Narrative, hath been frequently found ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry fallible; a conſiderable inſtance where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of is, that after the extracting a Tooth from — it could not reſtrain the ſlight flux following it; I ſay, the firſt and infant reputation of this <hi>Gallique tincture,</hi> and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count given the Publique of its monſtrous effects and ſucceſs, doth for the moſt part oppugn what I have here alledged to diſparage that way of Reſtriction, and would unanſwerably confute it, if it were able to ſupport its own reputation. The Medicine is rationally compoſed, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerves well, but not ſo much applauſe as its Author aſſumed.—</p>
            <p>The latter way of inducing this choaking Coagulation, is by manual operation; that is by the uſe of Buttons, Doſſils, Ligature and Compreſs, or holding the Thumb or Finger on
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:106833:25"/>the Orifice ſo long, till the bloud for want of motion coagulate, all which are not with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out their great inconveniencies and diſap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointments, as to Ligature and Compreſs thereby. I have juſt now ſufficiently anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipated any Objections here: you may pleaſe to remember, that <hi>Mr. Hobbs</hi> furniſhed me with an inſtance to the diſcredit of But<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tons, &amp;c. for that they ſometimes bury them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves amongſt the Muſcles and <hi>Eſchars,</hi> as he found once at <hi>St. Bartholomews Hoſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal,</hi> in a ſtump ſent from Mr. — where thoſe Engines which had been applyed to choak the Veſſels had ſlipt up the interſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of the Muſcles, and ſeemed to him (when he firſt felt them) to be ſmall ſhot; ſo that to a plain ſtump, they had the kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly acceſſion of a ſinuous Ulcer or two, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracted by their having laid there ſome con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderable time, the member being taken off at Sea. I find complaints of this nature, and cautions thereupon given us,<note place="margin">page 304.</note> by <hi>Mr. Woodal.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The latter way of the Finger or Thumb: is famous for the effect it had on one of the former <hi>Princes of Orange,</hi> of which my <hi>Lord Bacon</hi> gives an account.<note place="margin">Sylv. Sylv. cent. <hi>1.</hi> experim. 66.</note> It being al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo uſed at this day to ſmall and deſpicable <hi>Hemorrhagies:</hi> to which ſort only it proveth effectual; it being difficult to imagine how
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:106833:26"/>it ſhould have ſuch proſperous ſucceſs on ſuch large Veſſels as are divided in the am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation of a member. It being very tedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, and while performing, the Wound muſt lie without dreſſing, open and expo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to the air; nor can it be ſuppoſed ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectual in the ſlighteſt aperture; if it be but either a little deep from the skin, or of any other form except what it hath, by being divided tranſverſly, that ſo the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion may be made fully and immediate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly upon it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The fourth general way of ſtopping the He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morrhagies of Wounds, is by the application of ſuch things as having a clammy, glutinous, gummy, glewy or the like nature; hardneth upon, and ſo choaketh the Orifice of the divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded Vein or Artery.</hi> Such are <hi>Roſin</hi> pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered, <hi>whites of Eggs, the hair of an Hare, Clay,</hi> all <hi>Earths,</hi> &amp;c. I would not, if I could, detract from the worth of that famous Powder of <hi>Galens,</hi> to which ſo many thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands have owed their preſervations. I will only ſay that none of thoſe Medicines, or any other operating the ſame way, can en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure competition with ours upon theſe ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral accounts.</p>
            <p>They anſwer not the intention ſo ſudden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly; Nor ſo ſurely,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> Nor ſo generally; for in ſmall
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:106833:26"/>deep Wounds, they do nothing to it as our Balſam doth; for if a Syringe-pipe can but enter into them to inject it, the flux is ſecured, as ſhall be anon confirmed.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fourthly,</hi> None of them produce any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther benefit to Wounds, not curable by conſolidation but reſtraining the flux, (of which they often fail); whereas this of ours incomparably digeſts, &amp;c. while it's al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo ſtopping the fluxes, as ſhall be more at large evinced in due place.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fifthly,</hi> All thoſe things, (eſpecially the whites of Eggs and Hares hair) when ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied to green Wounds and ſtumps: where no digeſtion being, no matter floweth to humect them; adhere ſometimes to the very wounded fleſh, always to the skin on the edges, whence they become difficult to remove without pain, and hazard of a new flux.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sixthly,</hi> All thoſe Dreſſings muſt be kept on long; thoſe immediately on the Ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices of the bleeding Veſſels, much longer, whereby thoſe pernicious effects are occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſioned, already ſaid to follow the like pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lix continuance of dreſſing to cure the bleeding of Wounds the third foregoing way.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The fifth manner of curing Hemorrhagies, is that of</hi> Ambroſius Pareus,<note place="margin">Lib. 10. cap. 3.</note> 
               <hi>by deligation of
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:106833:27"/>the Veſſel:</hi> a way always tedious, often ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſsleſs; and whatever vaunts the Author makes of it, it cannot be ſo ſecure as he pretends; it being liable, (ſometimes from the ſlackneſs, otherwiſe from the too great ſtraightneſs of the thred: ſometimes from its ſmalneſs, cutting through, or from its weakneſs, giving way) to a new flux when not ſo tolerable to the Patient, or ſo eaſily cured by the Artiſt as at firſt; Moreover, where two Veſſels or more bleed in one Wound, (which is very frequent) the one muſt be neglected, while the Liga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>is making on the other, it being no leſs impoſſible that two Operators ſhould be tying together at one Wound, than that one alone ſhould do it: nor is it eaſie to come at the ends of the Veſſels, becauſe they forthwith retire when divided. I for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bear to inſiſt on many of thoſe things, they being evident to every man's appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſion; nor on the tediouſneſs of finding them, nor the difficulty in ſeparating them from a concomitant Nerve, (where ſuch is.) The ligation of an Artery on other accounts, as in the Toothach, Epiphoras, Aneuriſma, &amp;c. is not hereby impugned.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A Sixth general Method for the ſtopping of the Hemorrhagies of Wounds, is by Sarco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks, or Incarnatives:</hi> ſuch are <hi>Aloes, Thus,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:106833:27"/>Pulv. Aſtringens Galeni, &amp;c.</hi> by which it's ſuppoſed, the mouths of the bleeding Veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels become covered and choaked with new begotten fleſh; but while this new fleſh is generating, they are in ſuch daily hazard of a new flux, that they dare not meddle with their Ligature, nor dreſſing in a te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dious while, nor much longer with that ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing immediately on the mouth of the Veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel; whence it's eaſie to gueſs what incarn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing there is like to be, perhaps ſuch putre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction is contracted by the deteſtable con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuance of one dreſſing, as ſhall conſtrain the Artiſt to pervert the courſe and inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Art, by uſing <hi>Mundificatives</hi> after <hi>Incarners,</hi> and <hi>Digeſtives</hi> after both. I pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume to tell you Sir, that I am not with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out reaſon if I affirm it a miſtake in thoſe, who ſuppoſe <hi>Galen's Powder</hi> doth by this way reſtrain a Flux; thoſe very few things things in it that are <hi>Sarcotick,</hi> are ſo ſatu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated by the whites of Eggs, and Hares hair, that they cannot influence their Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues, whereas they two alone without the commixture of thoſe Powders, ſhall do it; where then is the Incarnation? Neither is it ſenſe to ſuppoſe, that a doſſil dipt in an Incarnative Medicine, (ſuppoſe this to be ſuch) can beget fleſh, when it's not only diluted with bloud, but to operate on a
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:106833:28"/>part unprepared for it by digeſtion, &amp;c. (which ought to precede) and when per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps, to abide on the place ſix times lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, than any incarnate force remaineth in it.</p>
            <p>I do not deny, that the protruſion of the circumjacent fleſh, and the retiring of the divided Veſſels, and perhaps ſometimes a little Incarnation may choak and cover the ends of them which way ſoever the flux be reſtrained; but that being a <hi>Poſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fact,</hi> cannot properly be called a ſtopper of bloud, but a ſecurer of bloud ſtopt; for were it not atchieved before by the cloſing of the ends of the Veſſels, an <hi>extravaſation</hi> or new flux would follow; a memorable inſtance of which I ſhall relate in the thir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teenth Obſervation, where after the bleed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing had been ſtop'd ten days, and Incarna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>native Medicines to fill up the Wound had been uſed three; yet a ſtrong flux broke out, without any manifeſt cauſe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Seventh general way of ſtaying He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morrhagies is by revulſion and derivation:</hi> I put them together, becauſe their difference is very inconſiderable; and in this caſe are performed by one method, <hi>ſcil. Cups, Frictions, Ligature,</hi> and <hi>Phlebotomy.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Firſt,</hi> by being applyed to parts re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mote from the place bleeding, is ſuppoſed
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:106833:28"/>to give the bloud a motion (by drawing it) that way; this I confeſs in ſmall and internal <hi>Hemorrhagies,</hi> where applications are impoſſible to be made locally, may con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tribute much; but in the <hi>Hemorrhages</hi> which attend Wounds, being uſually large, they ſignifie very little being ſuch weak aſſiſters as are ſeldom uſed, never relied on.</p>
            <p>The <hi>ſecond</hi> being made on the extreme parts remoteſt from the <hi>Hemorrhage,</hi> are ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed not only to attract the courſe of the bloud that way, but ſo to inlarge and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtend the Veſſels, as to give them more ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacity to contain a quantity, exceeding their proportion, by which the tendency of the bloud towards the part wounded is not only diverted, but a great and redun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dant portion thereof, kept circulating in the part chaffed, (eſpecially if aſſiſted by Ligature) while the mouth of the bleed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Veſſel is ſecurely occluded; Frictions being ſuppoſed to keep at leaſt the due proportion of bloud, to the part where it's uſed, (wherefore it's ſo much uſed in <hi>Syncopes</hi> and <hi>regurgitations</hi> thereof on the heart); which being effected, it's eaſie to imagine, that the flux whereſoever it be, cannot much exceed the particular ſtock of the part where it is, which may be tole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable enough; becauſe after the <hi>Hemorrhage</hi>
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:106833:29"/>is ſecured; it may be ſupplyed by Detach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments from the reſt.</p>
            <p>The ſame anſwer given the former, is not impertinent to this: adding withal, that Fri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, by rarifying and heating the bloud, though but in one part, will yet have influ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence in the reſt: for in deſpight of this ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition, it will when ſo heated and attenu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ated, mix with the Maſs, and not a little ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſter that quality thereunto; whereby inſtead of impeding, it will conſiderably in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haunce the <hi>Hemorrhage.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>third,</hi> being made in the extreme and remote parts alſo; retains the bloud there, and compreſſing the Veins more than the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teries wholly impedes the return thereof: and yet admits (as far as the ſpring of the bloud is able to propel, and the capacity of the Veſſels to contain) a greater quantity than is proportioned; this is evident, on Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gature made for <hi>Phlebotomy,</hi> and the repleti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Veſſels upon it, whence the bloud is at once derived, revelled and fixed, and indeed a flux many times, if not wholly ſtayed, yet conſiderably rebated thereby, whence it becomes eaſie to ſtop by local applications; ſomewhat alſo is attributed to the pain cauſed by Ligature, which is ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed to attract (as they all do) to the place where they are made, and ſo derive
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:106833:29"/>the bloud from the part bleeding, as hath been often tryed, by painful tying the little Finger only, in an <hi>Hemorrhage</hi> of the Noſe; an other beſides this ſort of Ligature, is made alſo in Amputations to ſtay the flux, which may not be improper here to take notice of; for although (beſides ſome other uſes not pertinent to our preſent en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiry,) they ſeem to deſign only, to hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the deflux of the bloud to the part; yet they thereby alſo revel, by ſo turning its courſe another way, and thus all thoſe made immediately above the place of <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſion;</hi> and thoſe made remotely above that are advantagious, ſome men (and not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſs) uſing always three Ligatures in Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation, one on each ſide the diviſion, the other as far above it as the place will admit.</p>
            <p>I allow the Reaſon and uſe of all theſe Ligatures, and except againſt nothing they deſign; but that they are but partial ways, being unable alone, and of themſelves to cure, (though they for the preſent ſtop) an <hi>Hemorrhage,</hi> not being to continue with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out great hazard. (I once ſaw in an haſty Amputation the Ligature left on, which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gat ſuch horrible ſymptomes, as coſt the Patients life) there being alſo neceſſity to ſlacken them when your dreſs is in hand,
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:106833:30"/>that you may by the flux ſee where the ends of the bleeding Veſſels are, and diſpoſe of your applications accordingly.</p>
            <p>Sir, I hope it will not be altogether im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertinent, if I here take occaſion to recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend to the young Practitioner, one way of Ligature very uſeful in Amputations, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially above the Knee; that is to ſay, a wadd of hard linnen cloth, or the like, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide the Thigh a little below the <hi>Inguen,</hi> then paſſing a Towel round the member; knit the ends of it together, and with a Battoon, a Bedſtaff, or the like; twiſt it, till it compreſs the Wadd or Boulſter ſo very ſtrait on the crural Veſſel, that (the circu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation being ſtopped in them,) their bleed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing when divided by the Exciſion, ſhall be ſcarce large enough to let him ſee where to apply his Reſtrictives, nor ſhall the pain of that Operation be comparable to what it would be, were not the member nummed by the Compreſs. Yet I would direct him in all Conſtrictions, whether by gripe, nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row Ligature, or this we recommend, to ſlacken it a little before the application of his Dreſs, the better to find by their bleed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing where his care and applications are moſt needful; for want of this neceſſary Cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, poor Patients do often loſe much bloud unknown to the Chirurgeon, it ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:106833:30"/>lain conceal'd withing the encompaſſing bladder: nor is inartificial Ligature, and many thick pledgets and boulſters of leſs in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conveniency and miſchief; for that they often imbibe the extravaſate bloud, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cealing many large expences thereof.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>As to Phlebotomy,</hi> the laſt mentioned way of Revulſion and Derivation; it's alſo to be made on the remoteſt part from that bleed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, by which it's ſuppoſed to give the bloud a motion that way, and ſo derives its courſe from the part wounded, and by emptying the Veſſels, ſlackens and rebates its efflux, from thoſe that are hurt. This doth eminently contribute even in fluxes from Wounds, where there is a <hi>Plethora ad vaſa,</hi> a repletion of the Veſſels, and is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comparably uſeful in <hi>Hemorrhagies</hi> from in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal Ruptures, penetrating Wounds, <hi>Hae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moptyſis, Hemorrhagies</hi> from the Noſe, <hi>hemor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rhoidal Veins</hi> or <hi>Womb,</hi> &amp;c. but in any other circumſtances it's ſo far from being ſervice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, that it begets miſchief, and anſwers not the chief end and deſign of its uſe, no re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vulſion how plenary ſoever, being of its ſelf (without local application) able to ſtop a flux from a wounded Veſſel.</p>
            <p>So that briefly, it's always but a partial, ſometimes a needleſs, often a miſchevous way; the <hi>firſt,</hi> becauſe it only aſſiſts; the
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:106833:31"/>
               <hi>ſecond,</hi> when need to temperate Conſtituti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; the <hi>third,</hi> becauſe it hinders digeſtion, I mean in great Wounds, and moderate ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bits; but in bodies very plethorick, that have not bled ſufficiently at the Wound, whence the ſymptomatical Fever may be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come ſo high, as to beget a <hi>Phrenſy, Deliri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um, Hemorrhage,</hi> &amp;c. or that from ſome manner or circumſtance of the Wound (as large Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuſion, Laceration, Fracture, Puncture, &amp;c.) there be hazard of a <hi>Gangrene.</hi> It's very ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantagious, excepting to ſuch as are cauſed by a poiſonous Weapon or venomous bite, in which <hi>Phlebotomy</hi> is pernicious; for though it be for the moſt part an enemy to matu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, by rebating that heat which ſhould concoct the matter: yet in ſuch extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary caſes, where there is more matter than nature can overcome and digeſt, or that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of the plenitude of bloud, and vigo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous ſpirits (which when agitated in this work, would kindle and combuſt.) there would be danger of a too violent Fever, and other ill effects of the perturbation; It hath been found,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>River.</hi> lib. 17. ſect. 3. c. 1.</note> that the drawing off ſome thereby hath facilitated the work; but other ways, and moſt commonly bleeding retards it, as is evident from the deſign thereof, when uſed after Contuſions, in <hi>Ecchymoſis, incipient Phlegmons,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>viz.</hi> to prevent their Apoſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation.</p>
            <pb n="33" facs="tcp:106833:31"/>
            <p>Of this, amongſt the forein Chirurge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons which in my Travels I have converſed with, <hi>viz. French, Hollanders, Portuguez, Spaniard, Italian, and Germans:</hi> the latter only have had the diſcretion to be ſenſible, and ſo highly are they ſo, that they will ſcarcely allow of <hi>venae ſection,</hi> though very urgent ſymptomes that might be remedied thereby, have called for it.</p>
            <p>It will be no impertinent digreſſion, if I inlarge this part of my Diſcourſe, by taking notice of, and reproving another deſign hereof in Wounds, and that is the curing or preventing the ſymptomatical Fevers at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending them, againſt which practice I ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject this <hi>Dilemma,</hi> That it either faileth of performing that intention, or by doing it, quite hinders and deſtroys Digeſtion, which being ever procured with a Fever, (as I have already ſuggeſted and proved) he that bleeds till that be taken away, muſt do it till all the bloud be extracted; this is manifeſt to any Artiſt, that hath obſerved how thoſe wounds from which ſo incredible a quantity of bloud hath been ſhed, as would tempt a man to believe it impoſſible for the flame of a Fever to find any fewel, have yet had that inevitable accident whileſt di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſtion hath been performing; this hath been often evident to me, particularly in
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:106833:32"/>the caſes to be mentioned in the Seventh and Ninth Obſervation, concluding this Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe: in both which, though the expence of bloud was monſtrouſly great, yet a ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry brisk Fever accompanied them, though the former by reaſon of his internal Wounds had been phlebotomized, and received ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral of the following draughts: ℞ <hi>Cryſtal. minerale</hi> 
               <g ref="char:dram">ʒ</g> j. <hi>Syr. Symphyt.</hi> ℥iſs. <hi>A<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> Sperm.</hi> R. <hi>Plant. Scabioſae. Papav. Rh. ana</hi> ℥j. <hi>miſce.</hi> Hence it's evident <hi>Phlebotomy</hi> cannot hinder the Fever;<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Thoſe are</hi> Aven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zoar, Fra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſtorius, Helmont, Angelus, Sala, Mich. Fehr. Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gius, Deu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſingius, Rolfinkius, <hi>and of our own Countrey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men. Dr.</hi> T. Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denham, <hi>Dr.</hi> Tob. Whitaker, <hi>p. 27, &amp;c.</hi> M. N. Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>del. Med. <hi>p. 408.</hi> G. Tomſon, <hi>cap. 7. Nor is D.</hi> Willis <hi>ſo fond of it, if his Diſcourſe be conſidered,</hi> c. <hi>15.</hi> de Feb. Sanguinis miſſio, ſi plethora adfit, — circa miſſionem ſanguinis inſtante variolarum eruptione, valde ambigitur. <hi>Of the ſame cautelous opinion is Dr.</hi> Sennertus de feb. <hi>l. 4. c. 12. and</hi> Riverius, <hi>lib. 17. ſect. 3. c. 2.</hi>
               </note> that it impedes Digeſtion, hath been already made good from the uſe and end of it, in <hi>Phlegmons, in fieri, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Let me further illuſtrate all this, by com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pariſon with the Small Pox, meerly putrid; in which <hi>Phlebotomy</hi> is ſo much decried, not only by the vulgar and illiterate, but by the men of Degree and Books: the one from fact and the frequent unſucceſsfulneſs there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, the other from reaſons in Phyſick, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong which what I have here alledged a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt it's uſe in Wound-Fevers, is not the leaſt.</p>
            <pb n="35" facs="tcp:106833:32"/>
            <p>I am not inſenſible of the many Authors,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>See Mr.</hi> Stubbs <hi>a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>againſt</hi> Tomſon, <hi>where you have them quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and urged at large from</hi> page <hi>172, to</hi> page <hi>258.</hi> Vide <hi>Dr.</hi> Willis, loc. cit. &amp; ubi dicit—interim cautio ſit, ne fermen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tationis ſeu efferveſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiae opus ullatenus cohibea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur, — &amp; River. Ubi Supra.</note> that by Advice direct, and by Obſervation confirm the benefit or harmleſneſs thereof. But it's rarely found ſo ſaving in hot Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treys, Flagrant Conſtitutions, Plethorick Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, (in all which the coctive heat is not weakned thereby, and yet the extrava<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gance of the matters quantity rebated, by which it is ſooner, and with more eaſe digeſted) and in all theſe e're coction be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan, it being equally hazardous, and unſafe to bleed in a digeſting Wound, in a ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>purating <hi>Plegmon,</hi> (that is large,) and in the <hi>Variolae</hi> that are cocting, and diſpoſed to extruſion, except in the unuſual, and extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinary circumſtances above-mentioned.</p>
            <p>The Fever accompanying the incipient <hi>Variolae,</hi> or Small Pox beginning, is ſymp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tomatical and neceſſary, and the <hi>Delirium</hi> that is ſometimes thereby occaſioned, very harmleſs, and what they ſoon recover when the matter is ripened and thruſt out; wherefore the moſt prudent and ſucceſsful Method I ever found, (having been concerned in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of that Diſeaſe) and that is practiſed by proſperous Women, are conſiderably hot: ſuch are <hi>Sack,</hi> and <hi>Saffron, Treacle-wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, Mithridate, Venice Treacle, Aqua Epide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mica, decoctions of Rue, Figs and Cochianel, Bezoar,</hi> &amp;c. whereby the Fever is inhaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed;
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:106833:33"/>but the Coction quickned and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patch'd: which when they find, and that the Pox appear well out, and the Fever decline, they abandon hot things, and uſe ſuch as are altogether temperate, having thereby framed and ſetled to themſelves this Rule, till the Pox are well out, you can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not uſe any thing too hot, nor afterwards things too<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>This,</hi> cum grano Salis.</note> cold. This is evident, that very few die of the Initial Fever, or any ſymptome concomitant with the Coction, except Phlebotomy have perverted the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention and deſign of Nature, by checking the Coction, or diſturbing the courſe they were in for expulſion.</p>
            <p>This I ſpeak, allowing ſtill the reaſon for bleeding in the former reſpects and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderations, and do apply the whole to Practice, in the caſe before us, <hi>viz.</hi> the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſtion, <hi>i. e.</hi> the maturation of Wounds: there being an identity in the Reaſons and Circumſtances. Therefore in temperate Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitutions, a due quantity and quality of blood, I am ſo far from bleeding, or gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving cool things, though ſymptoms have been brisk, and ſeemed to call for it, that I have adminiſtred, as well as applied Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſtions, (all which are hot) whereby aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſting Nature to overcome and coct the matter, I have ſooner than uſual took off
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:106833:33"/>the Fever, diſpatched the Digeſtion, and prevented the expence of much of my Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tients bloud, ſpirits and ſtrength.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The eighth and laſt general way of ſtopping the Hemorrhagies of Wounds, is by cloſing the Orifices of the Veſſels and uniting them.</hi> This is ſuppoſed to be done by all <hi>mild Vitrio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lates aluminous,</hi> and ſome Styptick, conglu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinating Applications, who from their aſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, drineſs and moderate ſharpneſs, ſhrink up the coats, and by that means conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pate the bleeding Veſſel; <hi>D. W. Needham,</hi> and <hi>M. Serjeant Wiſeman,</hi> ſeem to affirm this done by the <hi>A<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> Styptica</hi> R.<note place="margin">Num. 95.</note> as appears in their Narratives, publiſhed in <hi>Mr. Olden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burgh's Philoſophical Tranſactions:</hi> but whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they ſuppoſed it only, (their enquiry being whether, not how it ſtop'd the bleed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing) or delivered it on certain knowledge, is what I cannot determine from the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions made uſe of: nor whether any ſuch effect have been produced by any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Medicine ſave my own, which will be my next work to diſcover.</p>
            <p>Thus, Sir, I have finiſhed, and examined all the common ways of ſtopping bleeding: pardon my vanity, if I think I have ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed manifeſtly, that in many reſpects, they are moſt of them precarious and uncertain. whatever credit, long continuance, &amp;c.
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:106833:34"/>may have purchaſed for them. This I have attempted, not out of deſign the better to eſtabliſh my own, (a practice common with Innovators,) but on the ſincere ſug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſtions of Reaſon, Experience and Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, by all which every of my criminations are ſupported.</p>
            <p>There is another way very improperly computed by <hi>A. Pareus,</hi> and <hi>Dr. Read,</hi> amongſt thoſe of ſtopping the <hi>Hemorrhagies</hi> of Wounds, which is by dividing the bleed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Veſſel, that its ends ſhrinking up be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the muſcles, &amp;c. may become choak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed: but were this true, we ſhould behold its effects in Amputations, and have no flux in thoſe Wounds that divide the Arteries or Veins; but the contrary being evident, I have reaſon to ſlight it, as being alſo im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>practicable, and of no general application, or uſe.</p>
            <p>And now methinks I find my ſelf accoſted by the Critick, with this queſtion; If theſe are all the ways of ſtopping <hi>Hemor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rhagies,</hi> and that all of them are thus de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fective, and liable to ſo many ill conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quences: how comes it that ſo many large Fluxes are frequently reſtrained without the aſſiſtance of any other Method, or Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicament?</p>
            <p>My Anſwer is contained in the following
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:106833:34"/>conſiderations: That thoſe ways here ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected againſt, though they have ſtop'd <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morrhagies,</hi> have not done it with that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nignity and certainty as ours doth; for that great expences of bloud have been made, e're it hath been perfected.</p>
            <p>Many men have died of the ſymptomes and effects, not only of the loſs of the bloud, but thoſe ill applications, though they have not been noted, or obſerved as the cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes.</p>
            <p>I have no where affirmed them to be generally and in all reſpects fallible, that moſt of them have failed in large fluxes, is a known truth; that I never found mine ſo uncertain, but that I might rely thereon, (which can never be ſaid of the reſt,) is not a little ſure to me. Now on theſe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpects, though I have preferred my own, I have not ſo far diſparaged theirs, as to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny them wholly deſtitute of power to ſtay many <hi>Hemorrhagies:</hi> nor ſhould I my ſelf decline them, where I were denied my own; that man were certainly mad, that would rather be naked, than put on cloths much worn, or old faſhioned; things are every day improved, and more accommo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dated to our conveniency; the advantage of the latter, though it exceed and depre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciate, doth not altogether invalidate and
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:106833:35"/>make impracticable the former. The old way of Navigation, was to coaſt on the ſhoar, whereby a Voiage to <hi>Morlaix</hi> from hence, became at leaſt an hundred and fifty Leagues; but the Modern and improved way, by the advantage of the Compaſs, ſhortens it by at leaſt ſix ſcore: he were certainly a ridiculous Mariner that would ſlight that advantage, and he no leſs that being ignorant of its uſe, or in impoſſibility of having the benefit thereof, would de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cline his Voyage, rather than purſue it the old way.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>My Second general <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ndertaking, was to ſhew the way how I conceive, our Balſam ſo ſuddenly, and ſometimes without Ligature, ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cureth Hemorrhagies.</hi> In order to which I ſhall firſt relate divers Obſervations and Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periments made of <hi>Oleum Terebinthinae,</hi> and humane bloud, and the various <hi>Phaenomena</hi> thereof, and then from thence deduce proofs for which I ſhall preſume in this Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Experiment </seg>I</label> Take Oil of <hi>Turpentine;</hi> heat it, and ſpread it on a planed board, or other Tim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber; the ſubtil volatile parts thereof: ſome exhale, others inſinuate thereinto, leaving the gummy reſinous fixed part behind, which becomes a very firm, tough and adhering inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument, and is commonly called <hi>Varniſh,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:106833:35"/>ſo uſed, to keep the wood from cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupting by the Air, or from Worms: Pain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters for that reaſon alſo tempering their Colours therewith, eſpecially the brigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ones; for then though not heated, it ſoon hardeneth, as doth Lin-ſeed Oil, and without becoming yellowiſh, as that doth.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Experiment </seg>II</label> Dip your little Finger (firſt waſhed clean, and dryed) in reeking bloud of an Artery; and then in hot Oil of <hi>Terebinth.</hi> and they ſhall ſoon become like a tough skin, or covering thereunto: ſo contracting or ſhrinking, as to beget a ſenſible griping or ſtraitneſs thereon, and will not eaſily re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>move without Oil, or ſome unctuous body.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Experiment </seg>III</label> Lay a drop, two, or three of hot Oil of <hi>Turpentine</hi> on a poliſhed Marble, or piece of clean ſmooth glaſs, and the ſpirituous volatile parts (of which it moſtly conſiſts) evaporating away, the remainder having at firſt expanded it ſelf, doth now manifeſtly ſhrink up: and (having at firſt application, by inſinuating to the little inſenſible Cavities thereof, a firm hold) endeavours as it were to contract it ſelf, and the ſubſtance to which adhereth; but its ſtubbornneſs will not yield to ſo weak a ſpring, but in fine cloth and ſuch pliable matter, it evidently ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects it; the reaſon hereof is very plain, its heat makes it more ſubtil and penetra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting,
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:106833:36"/>by which its rarified parts get in and faſten themſelves to the matter on which it lieth, and by that heat gently exhaling its volatile parts, which being the moſt of its quantity, the more tough and gummy re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mains, endeavour to contract, to ſupply the evaporations of their finer particles: in which attempt, being in their circumfer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence faſtned firmly (as all reſinous bodies aptly are) to the matter on which they lodg, they contract that alſo, if it be ſoft and flexible enough to yield to that action.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Experiment </seg>IV</label> Heat an ounce of <hi>Oleum Terebinthinae,</hi> in a bloud-porringer that would hold three ounces: let a Vein, or an Artery bleed it full, and you ſhall find the bloud inſtantly to coagulate, not a looſe frangible crud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling as Acids produce therein; but a more tough, faſt, and as it were gummy conden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation; let it ſtand a while, and the Oil ſhall all of it ſeparate and ſuperſide: the longer it ſtands, the harder the bloud grows, eſpecially the Surface, which will become very tough. This Experiment I made many times: and (which is very remark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able) always found it without any <hi>Serum,</hi> though the reſt of the bloud drawn ſimply, and ſet to cool in other Porringers, did a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bound therewith: now view this conden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed blood by a Microſcope, and it appears
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:106833:36"/>very firm, compact, cloſe and opake; but the other, though ſevered from it's Serum, ſhews thin, and almoſt tranſlucid; that crud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led by a ſolution of <hi>Vitriol,</hi> looks like a heap of looſe black dirt, or gravel: the former only reſembling black Pitch, by which that it's fitteſt for the performance, we ſhall by and by diſcover.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Experiment </seg>V</label> After the bloud ſo condenſed hath ſtood two hours or thereabouts with the Oil upon it; the ſurface of the bloud be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes whitiſh, view this alſo through the Glaſſes, and you will find there to be a num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of light ſpots, on the rim thereof, having various ſhapes and figures, neither round, ſquare, nor regular. I endeavoured to move it with a Needle, whilſt mine eye was on it through the Tube, by which I diſcovered it to be a colour of the ſuperfi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cial bloud, not any milky ſeparate matter, as I apprehended.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Experiment </seg>VI</label> At the ſame time, thruſting the point of the Needle through the Surface, and lift<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it up, to ſee how far that whitiſhneſs continued, beyond the rim of the bloud; I found it no deeper than the upper skin: but what was very obſervable, the Needle though fine pointed: when I lifted up the Surface therewith, came not through it by one diviſion thereof, as it did in other
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:106833:37"/>coagulations; but forcing up the hardned ſuperficies, it broke at ſome diſtance round about it, ſo that a flap was thereby made like a Trap-door, or a Valve: which upon withdrawing my Needle, fell into its place again: A clear proof of its being very firm and tough.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Experiment </seg>VII</label> This coagulated bloud, made ſo by Oil of <hi>Turpentine,</hi> is a moſt incomparable Bal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſam, to heal Wounds by Conſolidation, or to digeſt and incarn thoſe that require it. It's known that internal Wounds and Ulcers, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing incapable of local application, are cured by vulnerary Dyets; which, ſay the Learned, is by hightning and improving the Balſam of the bloud. Now to make it a good Topical Balſam, I think nothing exceeds the celebrated Oil of ours: as any one that will experiment it, may eaſily aſſure himſelf: for though there be no ſenſible commixture; yet after the ſubſiding bloud is freed from the Oil ſwimming a top of it: yet by the ſmell it appears conſiderably impregnated therewith.</p>
            <p>Sir, I want leiſure to make other trials, neceſſary to a full diſcovery, and ſolution the Queſtion, how this Medicine ſtops <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morrhagies</hi> of Wounds. Thoſe here given you, are all I have been able to make, ſince your Commands have been upon me:
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:106833:37"/>there are a few more, which I would re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commend to the examination of the Curi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous; and which I ſhall attempt, as I have opportunity, and give you account of the ſucceſs.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> I would try whether hot <hi>Oleum Terebinthinae</hi> doth not ſenſibly occlude the aperture of an Artery, or Vein, by taking the <hi>Crural,</hi> or <hi>Carotid</hi> ones of a Dog, and making Ligature on the further part, would there divide it, and draw out the untied end as far as it would come, ſtopping its bleeding, by a compreſs of my Thumb and Finger: and ſo dip it in the hot Oil, ſlackning my compreſſure to let ſome of the bloud flow: after which totally ſtopping it for a time would then repeat the tryal, till I found how long after its immerſion therein, it would be, before it ſo firmly cloſeth, as of it ſelf to retain the bloud. I would then alſo examine, whether any U<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nition were confirmed; how long it's a do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; whether the bloud coagulate within the Orifice; and by ſo oppilating it, contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute to the ſtay of the <hi>Hemorrhage.</hi> I would alſo in one day amputate the Thighs of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Animals of one ſpecies, and bind them up with dreſſing of <hi>Oleum Terebinthinae:</hi> every day afterwards, I would examine (even ſo exactly as with a <hi>Microſcope</hi>) how
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:106833:38"/>Nature works, what ſhe is doing, and hath done, in the ſeveral parts of that time to the divided Veſſels, to ſecure their flow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</p>
            <p>I would alſo by Punctures, oblique, and tranſverſe inciſions of the Arteries; and which is worſt, by tonging them as boys do Reeds, to make muſick with: try if if they would not be cloſed by this Oil; how it's effected with the different ways and ſteps Nature takes to atchieve it; theſe I would recommend to the men of leiſure and Curioſity; as alſo the re-examination of thoſe tryals I have made, deſiring them, if in one or more, they find not all things to agree with my account, they would re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peat them, conſidering they may ſometimes fail, by reaſon of a different craſis in the bloud, from ſome fault in the Oil, or ſome other unknown occaſion, (perhaps his own perfunctory attempts) with this patience and Ingenuity,<note place="margin">Eſſay the ſecond, of unſucceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riments, <hi>page</hi> 107. <hi>Edit.</hi> 2.</note> Mr. <hi>Boyle</hi> tried ſome ſuch related Experiments of the Lord <hi>Bacon,</hi> and Sir <hi>Thomas Brown;</hi> and though after divers repetitions he found they did not ſucceed, yet at laſt had his expectations gratified.</p>
            <p>From all the aforeſaid appearances, it ſeems probable to me, that our Balſam doth thus reſtrain <hi>Hemorrhagie;</hi> firſt on its appli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, it contracts the bleeding Orifices:
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:106833:38"/>
               <hi>Exper.</hi> ſecond and third, begetting alſo that firm Coagulation of the bloud, <hi>Exper.</hi> firſt and fourth, and that not externally only, but internally alſo; by the former it conſtipates, by the latter it chokes and oppilates them: that externally aſſiſting alſo to the griping the end, or aperture of the bleeding Veſſel, and thereby ſtrengthens the occluſion, the bloud being unable to penetrate it, by <hi>Exp.</hi> the ſeventh; it's probable the <hi>Coagulum</hi> heal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth up the Orifice of the bleeding Vein or Artery, either by uniting the Coat, or by Concarnation, <hi>i. e.</hi> begetting ſome interme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diate ſubſtance, which it will nimbly do, being internally and externally lodged up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on it.</p>
            <p>This, Sir, is the beſt Mechanical account I can give, or apprehend of the matter. I hope by future tryals of my own, or ſome more intuitive Experimentators, I may be confirmed in this opinion concerning it; or that a truer ſolution thereof (if ſuch can be) will be dilucidated.</p>
            <p>Whether the actual heat of the Medicine, may not contribute eſpecially to the ſhrivel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the wounded Veſſel, is to me no doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful queſtion; having found on the cold ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication thereof, thoſe effects were not produced: from whence I would alſo in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer, that the firſt mentioned Experiments
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:106833:39"/>operated on the bleeding Veſſel, accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to my Explication of them, ſince with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the actual heat neceſſary to cauſe thoſe <hi>Phaenomena,</hi> the bloud is not ſtayed; <hi>Ergo,</hi> it muſt be ſtopped either by the immediate effect of its actual heat, or thoſe mediate ones, related in the firſt Experiments: or (as I am inclined to believe) by a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>currence of both.</p>
            <p>Whether the adſtringing quality, aſcribed to the <hi>Turpentine tree,</hi> by<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Lib. 8.</hi> de Simp. med. fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cult.</note> 
               <hi>Galen,</hi>
               <note n="†" place="margin">Lib. 1. cap. 72.</note> 
               <hi>Dio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcorides, Laguna, Gerard,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Cortex, folia, &amp; fructus ejus, adſtringunt,</hi> have here any juvancy, I know not. There ſeems to be a <hi>ſtypticity</hi> in the Oil it ſelf, when rubbed between the Fingers: of what uſe here I leave to other Judgments.</p>
            <p>If the whiteneſs appearing, <hi>Experiment</hi> 5. be a tendency of the bloud to matura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, it's a ſtrong evidence of the dige<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtive faculty of our Balſam.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>My third general deſign, is to give ſome directions to be obſerved in the choice and uſe of this Medicine.</hi> As to the former, I am to acquaint my Brother Chirurgeon, that there is no eſſential, though there be a reputed difference, between what is cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led by ſome the <hi>Spirit,</hi> and by others, the <hi>Oil</hi> of <hi>Terebinth;</hi> they being names promiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuouſly given to one and the ſame kinds
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:106833:39"/>of thing, when in reality they are<note n="*" place="margin">See Mr. <hi>Febure,</hi> part. 2. lib. 2. ſect. 10. cap. 19.</note> all Oils, as is evident by their ſwimming on water, wherewith they will alſo commix upon ſhaking together in a Phial, and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver again upon ſtanding a while, as in the <hi>Aq. Gonorrhea Quercetani;</hi> the firſt running in the diſtilling <hi>Turpentine</hi> being a thin limpid ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, induced<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Tyroc. chym.</hi> lib. 2. c. 4.</note> 
               <hi>Beguinus</hi> and<note n="†" place="margin">
                  <hi>Inſtit. Med.</hi> lib. 5. part. 3. ſect. 3. c. 5.</note> 
               <hi>Sennertus,</hi> ſo to denominate it; but our Colledge more truly, <hi>Oleum tenue &amp; album, inſtar aquae;</hi> the <hi>Auguſtans</hi> and<note n="*" place="margin">De oleis chym. di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtil.</note> 
               <hi>Erneſtus,</hi> the white Oil and<note n="†" place="margin">
                  <hi>Comp. Chym.</hi> ſ. 2. c. 7.</note> 
               <hi>Monſ. Glaſſier,</hi> the Aethereal Oil of <hi>Terebinth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But though they are all Oils, they are not all alike ſo: for when diſtilled accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the way of the <hi>Auguſtan</hi> Diſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſatory, and that directed by <hi>Glaſſier ubi ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pra,</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Tyroc. Chym.</hi> l. 2. c. 6.</note> 
               <hi>Beguinus, Euonymus,</hi>
               <note n="†" place="margin">
                  <hi>Theſau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rus,</hi> page 314.</note> 
               <hi>Philiatrus, Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtus,</hi> (which is R. <hi>Terebinthinae pellucidae quantum volueris, diſtilletur lento igne per re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tortam ſ. a.</hi>) there comes firſt <hi>Oleum Album, ad quod ſequitur flavum, &amp; ultimo rubrum</hi>— but when done according to our <hi>Phar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macopoea, Sennertus</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Ubi Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pra.</note> 
               <hi>inſtitut.</hi> And one way of <hi>Erneſtus,</hi> by putting four times its quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tity of water into the Alembick there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with; there cometh little other than this white Oil; the former is queſtionleſs the beſt way, (only incident to <hi>Empyreumat.</hi>) and the laſt red Oil coming thereby, the
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:106833:40"/>chiefeſt for our purpoſe; next to it is the yellow, and where neither is to be had, the oldeſt white Oil is to be preferred, becauſe its fiery particles are ſpent, and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vaporate in age, eſpecially if not cloſe ſtopped, or have been often opened; the <hi>Empyreuma,</hi> if any be in either of them, is no impediment to, but promotes its con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtringency, though perhaps it may hinder its digeſtive influences.</p>
            <p>Yet in aged cold phlegmatick bodies, and parts mortified by the expence, or defect of vital heat, I ſhould prefer the firſt and moſt ſpirituous white Oil, which is that moſt commonly ſold by the Druggiſt, though in hot flagrant Conſtitutions abounding with Choler, heat, and ſharpneſs of the bloud, I ſhould chuſe the other, as being more balſamous, and leſs biting, and hot.</p>
            <p>I have ſome reaſon to doubt, that the Chymiſts do often abuſe us, in the Oil commonly ſold us for a leſſer price by far than the <hi>Terebinth,</hi> from which it ought to be drawn: there is a baſe <hi>Turpentine</hi>-like ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance called commonly <hi>Terebinth,</hi> brought from <hi>France,</hi> drawn from the Fir and other Trees, much uſed to this purpoſe, which is no more the gum of the <hi>Turpentine</hi> tree, than Tar is. It were to be wiſhed, care were uſed to prevent thoſe great abuſes in
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:106833:40"/>Chymical preparations, the publick Elabo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratory, new ſet up by the Apothecaries Company in <hi>London,</hi> is a deſign of great utility and publick advantage, which may in time ſecure us ſuch Medicines as may be relied on.</p>
            <p>The Directions neceſſary to be regarded, and followed in the uſe of this Medicine, to Wounds, pleaſe to receive thus promiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuouſly, as they occur to my memory.</p>
            <p>And <hi>firſt,</hi> I muſt not forget to tell you, that it ought to be very hot, and more, or leſs ſo, according to the urgency of the flux, the temper of the Patient, the quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs or flatneſs of the Spirits, and native heat of the part; and becauſe in heating it, it is very apt to flame, and when ſo, is difficultly extinguiſhed. I always in Ampu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations or large Wounds, have two Veſſels with the Oil in them, ready heated; that if one kindle, the other may ſerve. I do alſo heat it on glowing, coals, that have no flame, and in a broad deep Veſſel, that may ſufficiently intercept the force of the fire, from kindling the exhaling ſpirits.</p>
            <p>This circumſtance, Sir, ſeems to render it difficult, if not impoſſible to be uſed in the great fights at Sea; partly from the hazard and inconvenience of fire; partly from the tediouſneſs of heating it, and the aptneſs
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:106833:41"/>to flame, while ſo heating, which would be very perilous; to remedy, and prevent all which, I have conſidered of a very effectu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al way: which is to have a Copper Veſſel, with a long neck, flat bottom, and a nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row mouth, like a chymical Matraſs, or Bolts-head, to which I would have, either a cloſe ſtopper, or a Cover, ſo exactly fit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, that the ſpirituous parts of the Oil ſhould not by continual heat evaporate a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way; this would be kept in due heat by a very little fire, not more than is neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to heat Cauterizers, and without any danger of flaming; nor would its continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance on the fire, rebate its vertue; for by the Veſſels being cloſed, as I have ſaid, the Spirits and evaporative parts, would only circulate therein. Some few of the more vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latile would be ſpent upon every opening it, which however might not be inconvenient, ſince by diſcharge, the Medicine is not ſo potentially hot, and thereby fitter for re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent ſimple Wounds: by this means having it always ready, it's but to pour a neceſſary quantity into a Porringer or other conve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nient Veſſel, at the time you are ready to uſe it: the different particular ways of which I forbear here to recite, becauſe in the Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtories or Obſervations, they will be ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently related.</p>
            <pb n="53" facs="tcp:106833:41"/>
            <p>There are two neceſſary Concomitants, when our Medicine is uſed, to reſtrain a flux: they are Ligature, and an encompaſſing Defenſative, <hi>ex bolo,</hi> &amp;c. and moiſtning the bandage in <hi>Poſca.</hi> This I ſpeak with re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect to Amputations, or great Wounds: in which it cannot be imagined, that without the former to compreſs, retain and conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue the Applications, a due and neceſſary time, the work can be effected, or the wound preſerved from accidents without the latter: more eſpecially, I would direct to deliga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the member, to be amputated ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording as I have already ſaid; that the greatneſs of the flux being impeded there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by, might not dilute the Medicine before it can perform its intention, or come intirely on the part bleeding, to reſtrain it: for which end, there rarely appears any occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion to uſe it more than once: for any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther deſign, as the quickning the ſenſe of a part, reviving benummed <hi>Paralytick Nerves:</hi> it may be uſed oftner, as alſo to quicken dull digeſtion; but then I ſuppoſe it beſt, to mix it with other temperate things of the like quality; as <hi>Linimentum Arcei, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>n<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guent. Baſilicon, Ol. Hypericonis, Lumbrico<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum, Catulor.</hi> &amp;c. except a flux of bloud, or <hi>Synovia,</hi> require its intire application.</p>
            <p>Which may be indifferently made to all
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:106833:42"/>parts: thoſe near, the Eyes only excepted; for it's of ſo diffufive and inſinmuating a qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, that if applied near them, it will work in and occaſion much pain and inflamation, wherefore in Wounds about the forehead, great care ought to be to prevent its de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcent thither. I once ſaw much pain and trouble thereby unluckily alighting upon a cholerick perſon, to whom theſe, as all other hot applications, are very uneaſie.</p>
            <p>Though I never had occaſion but once, to employ it by way of dreſſing to the breaſt; yet cannot find any reaſon in my own judgment, or that obſervation to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuade me therefrom, if the aforeſaid occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions needed it. What ſeems to render it unſafe to that part (I ſpeak of penetra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting Wounds thereof) is its heat or bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terneſs; on account of the former, where a <hi>Pleurizy, Peripneumonia,</hi> or the like is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comitant, it ought to be forborn; but this is ſo rare a Congreſs, that I think ſcarce in a man's time, ſhall it occur to him in pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice; its bitterneſs is ſo very inconſider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, that from thence cannot any Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment be drawn to deter from its applica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, where need requires ſuch a Medicine; and not a better grounded Objection ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears to oppoſe it. I am ſure it's a very con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderable<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Charas. Pharm.</hi> R. part 3. ſect. 1. c. 42.</note> 
               <hi>Pulmonick,</hi> commended by
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:106833:42"/>
               <note n="†" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pharm. Rationalis.</hi> part. 2. ſect. 1. cap. 6. c <hi>Tyroc. Chym.</hi> l. 2. c. 4.</note> 
               <hi>Dr. Willis,</hi> in <hi>Phthiſis,</hi> and by <hi>c Begui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus,</hi> in Coughs, <hi>Orthopnoea,</hi> &amp;c. Curing alſo Ulcers in the Lungs: on all which accounts it's made the <hi>Menſtruum</hi> of the common <hi>Balſamum Sulphuris,</hi> and the <hi>Balſamum Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hectica</hi> of <hi>Paracelſus.</hi> I have alſo in pene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trating wounds of the Breaſt, given divers times, ſome drops thereof in a proper Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hicle, by which I have evacuated much matter by Urine, bettered the digeſtion of my Wound, and rebated the conflux of humors, by deriving them diuretically. <hi>Dilatat pectus, &amp; abſtergit,</hi>
               <note place="margin">In concil. wittichii conſ. <hi>30.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>&amp; per urinam (quod maximè in hoc caſu competit) promovet,</hi> —ſaith <hi>Schroderus</hi> of a preparation of <hi>Turpentine.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If the Veſſel bleeding be large, and the flux impetuous, as the <hi>Crurals</hi> when Ampu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation is made above the knee: then I lay large buttons of Tow dip'd therein on the ends of them. In moſt other Stumps, I leave all to a large Pledget or two, of a reaſonable thickneſs, which being immerſed in the ſame, and applied over all, I lay one or more of the like Pledgets, armed with the common reſtrictive of <hi>Bole,</hi> &amp;c. together with bladder and bandages, moiſt with wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter and Vinegar.</p>
            <p>In Stabs and narrow Wounds, penetrating the fleſhy parts of the Thigh, Leg, Arms, &amp;c.
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:106833:43"/>where by reaſon of a Vein or Artery hurt, a great <hi>Hemorrhage</hi> enſueth. I would in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject my <hi>Oleum Terebinthinae</hi> made duly hot, till the whole Cavity were replete there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with, and there retain it, by ſtopping the Orifice or Orifices with my hands a few hours, by which it would become undoubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edly ſecured.</p>
            <p>I have ſometimes the next day after this Medicine of ours hath been applied, found the edges of the Wounds and Stumps bli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtered as far as the Pledgets have extended, the bladders of which have been filled with a milky matter; the cauſe thereof I always found to be, the too hot application of the Medicine, when haſte hath prevented con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration, and occaſioned its being ſo ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied; and to a perſon of a very hot con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution, the white matter filling thoſe little veſications, though thin, is the ſtrong digeſtive effect of its cauſe. I never much regarded them, other than to ſnip them with my Sciſſors, and lay on it a little <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>n<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guent. Album Camphoratum,</hi> which drieth them by the next day; wherefore thoſe to whom the appearance may be ſtrange and ſurprizing, have no reaſon to be diſcouraged thereat, or afraid to uſe the Medicine after this intimation; nor to apprehend it gan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grenous, as one lately did, and uſed a <hi>Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>xivium</hi>
               <pb n="57" facs="tcp:106833:43"/>to cure it, though he were no ſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger to the uſe of the Oil, to this end. Other ill effects I have ſcarce found, (except the ſymptoms in the laſt obſervation were ſuch;) but that thoſe Wounds to which I have applied it, have been as eaſie as my others, to which I had not uſed it.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, To amplifie and perfect one Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riod, which upon a review I find defective, I muſt inculcate my direction, that where digeſtion, more than conſtriction is deſign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and in all young hot cholerick Conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutions, I prefer the oldeſt thickeſt Oil, and which ſmells leaſt; but where a ſtrong coagulation is neceſſary, becauſe a large Veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel is hurt, or where a <hi>venene gangrenous Sanies</hi> is to be corrected, and abſumed, where the part is afflicted with a cold diſtempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rature, <hi>Convulſion, Palſey, Inſenſibility,</hi> and of debilitated heat, then the thinneſt and moſt ſpirituous.</p>
            <p>The ſtrong ſmelling Oil is the moſt per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinent. Theſe warm productions of this Balſam, ſeem liable to an Objection, which you ſhall find made, and anſwered in the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion of the laſt Obſervation.</p>
            <p>The reſtraining <hi>hemorrhagies</hi> of Wounds, was what principally occaſioned this re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commendation of <hi>Oleum Terebinthinae:</hi> I will now, Sir, endeavour to illuſtrate its
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:106833:44"/>Vertues for Wounds, in a more generous ſenſe, by enquiring into the many other benefits acquired by it, without reſpect to their bleeding, and this was the <hi>fourth</hi> task I laid upon my ſelf.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The firſt of which, is the ſtopping of the</hi> Synovia, <hi>or weeping of the divided Nerves and Lympheducts,</hi> which it doth by conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pating their little apertures. I believe no man that hath converſed with Wounds, and cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roding applications to them, but hath found a large gleet to flow from Wounds of magnitude and amputated Stumps; and the more the nearer to the Joint, the former being the lacrymation of the lymphatick Veſſels and Nerves, the latter, the efflux of the Joint <hi>Serum:</hi> and both of them ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times to that degree as to wet the bandage, though large, and the pillow on which the member may reſt, as much as if a quart of water or more had been thrown thereon. It were too large and beyond the bounds, both of my brains and Letter, to diſcourſe either of the Controverſies,<note place="margin">Againſt which <hi>Is<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brandus, Demerbro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus, Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tom. oorp. human.</hi> l. 10. diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puteth at large.</note> whether there be a Liquor, and of what uſe both it, and the <hi>Lympha</hi> is; let it ſuffice to ſuggeſt, that a great and famous Phyſician of our own, namely, the ever memorable <hi>Dr. Gliſſon,</hi> af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firms the former to nouriſh; and all agree, that it's the Vehicle, in which the ſenſitive
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:106833:44"/>ſpirits are conveyed, to furniſh the parts with motion and ſenſe, (or as one ingeniouſly calleth it, The Chariot of the ſenſitive Soul;) and that the Lymphatick<note n="*" place="margin">Idem in <hi>lib.</hi> 1.</note> Juice, humects, contemperates, &amp;c. Now being of uſes ſo eſſential to the ſubſiſtence of life, theſe conſequences do naturally flow; that the expence thereof, doth privatively diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpirit, conſume, debilitate, dry, inflame, &amp;c. and therefore that the ſecuring it from ſo exorbitant a profluence, is as neceſſary and beneficial, as the reſtraining the <hi>Hemorrha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gies</hi> of the Veins and Arteries; and this I will preſume to aver, is a faculty in Oil of <hi>Turpentine,</hi> tranſcendently above any other known Medicine, as is more eſpecially evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, in punctures of the Nerves, (where the weeping of that Juice, as that of a Vine when wounded, or Trees when tapped in the Spring, is very obvious and plain.) For the cure of which, it is become the infal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lible <hi>Arcanum;</hi>
               <note place="margin">A. Pareus, <hi>l. 10. c. 38.</hi> Fr. Sylvi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us de le Boe, nova Idea. part <hi>1.</hi> cap. <hi>42.</hi> parag. <hi>38.</hi>
               </note> when as before the diſcove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of that Vertue, the remedy of Punctures, was no better than either dividing the Nerve or tendon, or ſevering the member from the body, both which were not ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom prevented by Death.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly, It moſt excellently digeſts:</hi> a fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culty to which no other reſtrainer of bleed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing can pretend; and if both thoſe inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:106833:45"/>can be performed at once by one ſingle Medicine, (as they are evidently by this) how much time, pains, &amp;c. is ſaved to the Practitioner and Patient, and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently what value it is of, there needs no Argument to confirm this Poſition, it's ſo eaſie an Experiment, that every one may confirm it to his own ſenſe; nor doth it digeſt Wounds at the ill rate, moſt other Digeſtives do, which beſides that faculty, do alſo powerfully attract; ſuch are <hi>Crocus Terebinth. Vitel. ovor. Liniment. Arcei, Baſili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>con,</hi> &amp;c. whereby great expence of bloud and radical moiſture is occaſioned to the waſting the body, impairing the ſtrength, hindring the healing influences of the Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicine, macerating the wounded fleſh, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>getting <hi>Fungus</hi>'s, &amp;c. whereas this excellent Oil hinders the deflux of humors, digeſting the contuſed or extravaſate bloud, without drawing, or permitting the efflux of much more.</p>
            <p>Here, Sir, I muſt take notice of two Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jections to which this ſeems liable: That if <hi>Oleum Terebinthinae</hi> cloſe the mouths of the Veſſels, how can it digeſt, it being a Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culty inconſiſtent with that of Conſtrin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gents? or what ſhould it digeſt, ſince by its application, little or no matter extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vaſates for that faculty to work on? To
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:106833:45"/>this I reply, That though there be not ſuch large digeſtion, as is uſually produced by the aforeſaid applications, yet it doth maturate in a leſſer degree, what part of the bloud, <hi>Lym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pha,</hi> &amp;c. may be ſhed before application can be made; it being impoſſible to imagine, that the moſt quick and diligent applica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion thereof, can ſo prevent the efflux, but that ſome will get between the Dreſſings and the Wound, which coagulating about the mouths of the Veſſels, by capping, ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cures them; or it may be ſupplied with matter for the digeſtive faculty to work on, from the lacerated and frequently mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tified Fibres, or from what even in ſound members, and a healthful body, is by tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>colation extravaſate, and always lodging in the interſtices of the Muſcles, and their Fibres, and alſo of thoſe in the other Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neous parts.</p>
            <p>Moreover, It cannot be imagined, nor is it by me aſſerted, that the Veſſels are all of them, even the minuteſt, ſo wholly occluded, as that thin matter cannot extravaſate; but ſo ſufficiently done, and to that degree, as to ſecure a too liberal and extravagant effuſion of their ſeveral Liquors, and ferous Juices; to which may be added, that its reſtrin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gency is not by any manifeſt, or ſtrong Stypticity, but by the way and accidents,
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:106833:46"/>already explicated by the foregoing Expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riments.</p>
            <p>But to proceed: <hi>Thirdly, It is incompara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly the beſt Balſam to heal Wounds of the Nerves,</hi> to which it ſeemeth ſo particularly adapted; that as it ſeldom faileth of doing it, ſo nothing elſe hath been hitherto found to come near it in that quality, ſaving as they have more or leſs thereof commixed: Every one is ſo much an Anatomiſt, as to know that it's difficult, if not impoſſible to make a Wound (great enough to deſerve the name) without hurting ſome branches of the Nerves, they being ſo thickly diva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ricated into all the parts of the body (the Lungs excepted) ſome being of a belief, <hi>that the skin is a fine woof of Capillary Nerves,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>I.B.</hi> Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>melus de corpore animato, <hi>lib. 4.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Veins, and Arteries, receiving into it the ends of the excretory Veſſels, ariſing from an infinite number of little Glandules.</hi> Now the whole <hi>Genus Nervoſum</hi> being the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veyers of ſenſe and motion, are vehemently aggrieved, when wounded, diſtorted, contu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, &amp;c. the former of which eſpecially, this Balſam pacifieth, and healeth no leſs won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfully, than evidently; by which <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vulſions, Palſeys,</hi> and other effects thereof are prevented and remedied; eſpecially thoſe direful ones, which follow their being pun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctured, as I have already intimated.</p>
            <pb n="63" facs="tcp:106833:46"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Fourthly,</hi> After Amputations, it hath one ſingular good effect above moſt other Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plications; that is the contraction of the Stump, keeping alſo the lips of large wounds from expanding to that degree, which more lax and ſoft applications admit, whereby the intention of croſs ſtitches is in part pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vented; this is done partly by hardening the lips of the Wound, (at which I would adviſe him that finds it, after the applicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of this Medicine, not to be concerned) but partly by the edges of the Pledgets, adhering to the lips of the Wound, when the ſpirits expiring contract them, accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the Second and Third Experiments. Hereby is prevented thoſe ghaſtly and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeemly ſwellings of Wounds, and ſpreading of Stumps: not that they ſtick ſo firmly, as to be obnoxious to the objections made againſt the like accident of glutinous Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plications, <hi>Page</hi> 14.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fifthly, It ſolely and perfectly healeth Pun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctures, and inciſed Wounds by Symphyſis;</hi> (where neither of them are very large), and that maugre its digeſtive Faculty. I know the ſame is performed by the appli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of moderate Aſtringents that have no Acids in them; but as ſuch cannot ſecure the <hi>Hemorrhagies</hi> that are large and deep, neither can they reach effectually to the bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tom
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:106833:47"/>of deep Punctures. Now that it may not ſeem ſtrange, I ſhall attribute a Power Conſolidative, to a digeſtive Medicine. I ſuggeſt, <hi>firſt,</hi> That Conſolidation is natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally performed; I mean, that Medicines do not actually unite Wounds: but by acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, <hi>viz.</hi> by one way or other, preventing or ſtopping extravaſation of the bloud, and Lympha, and reſiſting the influences of the ſurvening Air, both which would hinder unition: the one by humecting, the other by corrupting the divided Fibres, &amp;c. There being thoſe that ſpare not to affirm publick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, confidently,<note n="*" place="margin">G. Hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ron. Velſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chus. Cent. <hi>11th</hi> ob. Phyſ. Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicarum. Paracelſus Vuln. <hi>trad. 1. c. 14. Mr.</hi> Wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, <hi>page 346.</hi>
               </note> and perhaps very rationally, That the great and celebrated Cures, ſaid to be performed by the <hi>Sympathetick Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der,</hi> and the <hi>Magnetical <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nguent,</hi> are not beholden to them, but to the leſs regarded means, of keeping the Wounds clean and cloſe: ſo that our Medicine, though it do digeſt, yet by occluding the Veſſels, (as hath been ſhewn) it hinders extravaſation, and being gummous, defends from the Air, whereby it may be thought, as well to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolidate, as any other, ſince it doth as much as they, in preventing and defending from what would hinder it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> No Conſolidation was ever made altogether without Digeſtion; for it being impoſſible to reſtrain totally the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>travaſation
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:106833:47"/>of the bloud, &amp;c. It's ſenſleſs to imagine but that if the ſolution of Unity can be re-united, that matter muſt be di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſted, as is evident from what cometh off, though perhaps it be but little and not well cocted; and this uſually occurreth in deſpight of Applications, drying, and bind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, this though it may be not always diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge it ſelf at the Wound, is yet to be ſuppoſed, for that Nature either recovers it by aſſimilation; or as it is, introvaſates it, and ſo circulating with the bloud, &amp;c. is thrown out <hi>qua data via.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>The ſixth</hi> and laſt advantage of its ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication to Wounds, is, that it performeth all thoſe things, eſpecially reſtraining the fluxes of bloud, without the pain, burning, <hi>Synovia,</hi> prolixity, flux of matter, and all or moſt the other ill accidents attending, and already diſcovered in the other means and applications: I hope it's not improper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly called a Benefit, though it be but priva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tively ſo.</p>
            <p>And now, Sir, I am come to give you ſome particular and remarkable inſtances of the ſucceſsful effects, attending the appli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of this Medicine; which confirming <hi>de facto,</hi> all I have ſaid concerning it, I think is not Illogically placed here, it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing according to the method of late practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:106833:48"/>Writers, <hi>Willis, Wiſeman, Stubendorfi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us,</hi> &amp;c. which laſt named, in the concluſion of his Theory on the <hi>Scorbute,</hi> juſtifieth the pertinency of annexing Obſervations to ſuch Diſcourſes,<note place="margin">Sect. 49.</note> in theſe words: <hi>Nam ſi Galeno graviſſimo medicinae teſti credimus, non ſufficiunt ad exactam cognitionem univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalia,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Lib. 9. Method. cap. 6.</note> 
               <hi>niſi in exemplis &amp; particularibus una exercitemur, quod in iis, ut Galeni verbis u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tar, methodus, in his exercitatio conſiſtit.</hi>— Thoſe which I preſent you, ſhall be few and conciſe, though I have often uſed it in divers <hi>Hemorrhagies</hi> not here mentioned, and with the ſame proſperous ſucceſs, and that by Experiments on Dogs, &amp;c. Alſo by communicated obſervations, and by my own in divers Wounds and Amputations, made in this Hoſpital, I ſtill found it moſt happy and ſucceſsful, yet think it needleſs and too tedious here to recount them all: thoſe following being of different circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances, I have collected from the reſt.</p>
            <div n="1" type="observation">
               <head>
                  <hi>Obſervation</hi> I.</head>
               <p>A Man of a plethorick Habit, aged a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout forty years, was ſent to the Hoſpital from his <hi>Majeſtie</hi>'s Ship the <hi>Adventure,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſhot through the right Elbow with a Musket-bullet, which had lacerated the
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:106833:48"/>bones, and torn the Veſſels exceedingly; the member from the Wound downward, was <hi>Oedematous</hi> and ſenſleſs for want of a due influx, the Veſſel being ſo hurt. In ſhort, an Amputation became neceſſary, and I ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly took off the member in preſence of two Chirurgions, beſides my own peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, my Ligature and other preparations were common; after Exciſion, the bone be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing alſo divided, I covered the whole Wound with one well-made Pledget of fine Tow, dip'd in hot Oil of <hi>Terebinth;</hi> upon which I laid two more, armed with the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Defenſative, and bound it up <hi>S. A.</hi> dipping my Linnens in <hi>Poſca,</hi> taking off my Dreſſings the next day; I found the whole Wound look excellently well, with a white tendency to digeſtion; ſome little veſica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions were on the edges, but without ſmart or inflammation; thoſe I dryed up with <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>n<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guent. Album,</hi> firſt ſnipping them with my Sciſſors: I repeated my Dreſſing of <hi>Oleum Terebinthinae</hi> once more, and in a little time healed the VVound.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="observation">
               <head>
                  <hi>Obſervation</hi> II.</head>
               <p>About the ſame time, I was called to one <hi>Mr. Collings</hi> a Woolſted Comber, of ſixty five years old, who by a malignant Fever
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:106833:49"/>(under which he had laboured five weeks) was not only much emaciat, and diſpirit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, but had a confirmed <hi>Sphacelus</hi> of the right Leg, from the Knee downward. I was in company with ſome other Chirur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geons, when I was called to this Patient; and underſtanding the buſineſs, I invited them to ſee it. In their preſence, I made divers large and deep Inciſions, but neither ſenſe nor bloud appeared, but a very no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>xious ſcent. We all concurred in opinion, that a ſpeedy Amputation was to be made: while my Servants were preparing the Dreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, we diſcourſed the place where the work was moſt needful, and what applications were moſt proper; they adviſed the former to be done above the Knee, and the latter to be hot <hi>Egyptiacum,</hi> and ſpirit of Wine. I reſolv'd another courſe, for making my Inciſion a little above the uſual place, below the Knee, and there dividing the bones, I laid on two Pled<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gets, dip'd in very hot <hi>Oil of Turpentine,</hi> and common bandage over all: there iſſued a little grumous bloud after the Inciſion, and becauſe I found ſome remaining parts of the cadaverous fleſh, I touched the whole Stump with a cauterizing Iron, not to ſtop any flux, but to aſſiſt the exfoliation and ſeparation of the Sloughs, quicken the life of the part by ſo attracting the ſpirits, and
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:106833:49"/>killing any remaining venome and <hi>Sanies.</hi> The next day, having prepared <hi>Lixivium, ex. Abſinth. Scord. Rutae. Centaur. Ciner. Lig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor.</hi> cocted in Sea-water, and impregnated with Brandy; I fomented the Stump therewith, and dreſſed it again with my hot thin Oil of <hi>Terebinth;</hi> the next dreſſing I found the reliques of the <hi>Necroſis</hi> dryed up like a Cruſt, and conſiderably ſeparated from the quick fleſh, from whence I ſaw good to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kens of digeſtion; the old man was very couragious, I continued (in all four days) to dreſs with <hi>Ol. Terebinthinae.</hi> After ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, the Sloughs came all away, and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver did I ſee fairer digeſtion; but when the quick and ſenſible parts became naked by the exfoliation of theſe <hi>Eſchars,</hi> though my dreſſing were as benign and mild as could be, yet the ſmart and pain happen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to diſturb him of his reſt, under which his depauperated ſpirits were unable to ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt; he languiſhed to Death, though the wound altered not, and that I gave him high Cordials very liberally, with what elſe Art directed; I being very greedy of the recovery of ſo remarkable a Patient, after ſuch proſperous beginnings.</p>
               <p>That which made me prefer <hi>Oleum Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rebinthinae</hi> here, was the ſucceſs thereof in two ſuch caſes on a couple of young men,
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:106833:50"/>whom I had amputated in the mortified parts of both their Legs, and found that a ſoft Cautery and this Medicine, did incom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parably abſume the Sanies, and excited the ſpirits of the adjacent ſound parts, ſo as to induce a ſpeedy ſeparation and good dige<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion: My ſucceſs, I ſay with them, encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raged me to hope the like here; though theirs were both Legs taken off within twenty four hours diſtance, and not whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly quit of a ſpotted Fever, in which ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving been <hi>delirious</hi> on board the King's Ships, to which they belonged; they had either kept their Legs over the Hammacks, (it being a very cold Winter,) and ſo num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med and mortified them, or they became ſo from the ſtagnation of the bloud, the ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect of that coagulation, which highly ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nene Diſeaſes do uſually beget therein, if it be not carefully diluted, kept fluid, and in warm motion by proper Sudorifiques.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="observation">
               <head>
                  <hi>Obſervation</hi> III.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anno</hi> 1672. A Chirurgeon of this place (now dead) craved my adviſe concerning an <hi>Hemorrhoea</hi> that vexed him, in a very weak Patient, who had a <hi>ſinuous <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>lcer</hi> about the middle of the <hi>Tibia</hi> on the infide; the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vity of which ran under the bone, and aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cended
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:106833:50"/>obliquely towards the Knee, where probably (the matter being thin and ſharp) it had eroded an Artery, or a Vein, and begat this flux, which became intolerable to one ſo much extenuate as he was; I ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſed him to inject equal parts of <hi>Oleum Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rebinthinae,</hi> and a Decoction of <hi>Tormentil, Biſtort,</hi> and <hi>Knotgraſs-roots</hi> made in <hi>Styptick Wine,</hi> and to retain it from one dreſſing to another: which he accordingly did, and the bleeding moleſted him no more.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="observation">
               <head>
                  <hi>Obſervation</hi> IV.</head>
               <p>A Carpenter, by name <hi>Richard Sellar,</hi> looking up towards the top of an Houſe, whereon ſome Helliars were at work; by chance a ſhindle-ſtone falling down, alight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed on his face, and made a long deep Inci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, from the right Noſtril towards the Grinders: an Artery that was wounded thereby ſpouted out bloud, in as large a ſtream, as an ordinary Syringe-pipe could vent. I ſtop'd it with my Finger, whileſt my Servant warmed ſome Oil of <hi>Terebinth</hi> in a <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>vula ſpoon;</hi> when it was ready, I with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drew my Finger from the bleeding Artery, and it piſs'd out as before: I immediately poured the hot Oil upon it, which inſtant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſtop'd the bleeding like a Charm, and
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:106833:51"/>permitted me to ſtitch it up without any flux. When I had ſo done, I laid a Pled<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get of the ſame over the cloſed lips, and a Plaiſter upon it; the outward lips ſoon conſolidated, leaving no very apparent <hi>Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>catrix;</hi> the inſide kept open ſomewhat lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, thereby expediting the unition of the outward part, by which a very fine ſeam was made.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="observation">
               <head>
                  <hi>Obſervation</hi> V.</head>
               <p>Shortly after this came to me a Woman, cut from the middle of the Noſe, down to the right end of the Mouth, by a Knife done by a <hi>Dutchman,</hi> who pretended ſhe had defrauded him; there iſſued ſuch a ſtream, as from the laſt mentioned, and was after the ſame manner ſtop'd, with no difference in it, or the ſucceſs; only that here a more <hi>inconſpicuous Cicatrix</hi> was induced, whether from the dry ſtitch which I here made, or the fineneſs of her skin; or becauſe the pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>netration of the Cheek was larger, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by the matter had a more liberal vent that way, I cannot determine.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="observation">
               <head>
                  <hi>Obſervation</hi> VI.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anno</hi> 75. I was ſent for to a <hi>Dutch</hi> Sea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man,
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:106833:51"/>who being gotten drunk, threw him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf into his Cabbin with all his Cloaths on: it unluckily fell out, that he had in his Pocket a ſharp-pointed Knife, ſuch as they uſually carry, and that it lay in ſo ill a poſture, that the weight of his body forced the point through ſheath and cloaths, and run up above three inches (entring a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the middle of the Thigh) obliquely towards his buttocks, ſo that the point might be an inch and half directly in from the skin, under which it lay; I drew it out, and found no part of it broken off; the Man complained of great pain, and there flowed much bloud: I then injected warm Oil of <hi>Turpentine,</hi> and put up above half-way, a thin <hi>Flamula</hi> dip'd in the ſame: then rouled him up, drawing alſo about ten ounces of bloud from the Arm. The man ſlept well all night; and after two days, I uſing nothing but a Pledget and a Plaiſter on the Orifice, the Solution being all uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, I let him walk about. I bled him becauſe he was plethorick, and I intended to heal the Wound by ſympathy.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="observation">
               <head>
                  <hi>Obſervation</hi> VII.</head>
               <p>A young melancholly Apothecary, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing diſappointed in an Amour, reſolved to
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:106833:52"/>deſtroy himſelf; in purſuance of which deſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate determination, he firſt ran his Sword through his body, entring on the left ſide below the heart, and paſſing out at the right oppoſite to it, wounded the <hi>Lungs</hi> and <hi>Mediaſtinum:</hi> the Orifices were ſmall, ſo that no blood iſſued from them, nor could I find much had been caſt into the breaſt. I bled him largely, and gave him ℞ <hi>Aq. Veronicae, Scabioſae, Sperm. Ranar. Plantaeg. an</hi> ℥<hi>i</hi>β. <hi>Lap. Prunella</hi> 
                  <g ref="char:dram">ʒ</g>j. <hi>Syr. de Meconio</hi> ℥j. <hi>Miſce.</hi> and appointed people to watch by him, and more eſpecially to keep from him any thing wherewith he might do himſelf more miſchief; he lay under great horrours all night, and in the morn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing by a cunning ſtratagem, (calling for his Breeches to give his Siſter a Key, he ſeemed willing to commit to her particular charge,) conveyed among the Bed-cloths a Pen-knife he had therein; which when all was quiet and without miſtruſt, he ran downwards into the hollow of the breaſt, from the upper end of the <hi>Sternon,</hi> think<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to make the ſame mortal Wound, they uſually do that way to young Pigs; but though he thruſt it as far as he could, it anſwered not his end, till all was diſcover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. By the large quantity of bloud that flowed from the Wound, I could not find
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:106833:52"/>that he had thereby hurt any internal part, or that any bloud was faln into the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vity of the <hi>Thorax,</hi> but that all iſſued from the Veſſels hurt in the containing parts, which I ſtopt with a ſmall <hi>Flamula</hi> dipt in the hot Oil, and had almoſt conglutinated the Wound, as alſo the foremoſt of thoſe in his breaſt in ſeven days: when (under continual horrors, deſperations, faſting and reſtleſneſs, he had ſpent that time, and brought himſelf very low) he died.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="observation">
               <head>
                  <hi>Obſervation</hi> VIII.</head>
               <p>A Plethorick Woman, by a Contuſion had her right breaſt apoſtumated; ſhe ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>purated it by a Cataplaſm of her own, (ſhe being one of thoſe Skil-leſs Midwives where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with the World is become peſtered.) She kept the Cavity ſo long open, by Tents and Salves of her own making, that it became <hi>cancerous:</hi> the Cavity was below her Niple about an inch and an half, towards her ſide, from which in one night, there iſſued a very large quantity of bloud, which ſhe diſcovered not until the morning, and in the ſurpriſe it begat, ſent to implore from me ſomewhat to ſtop it. I ordered her a little <hi>Aqua Styptica R.</hi> which ſhe uſed to no
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:106833:53"/>ſhe had bled monſtrouſly, and that the bloud was very florid, I thruſt a thick doſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſil of Lint, dipt in warm <hi>Oleum Terebin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thinae</hi> into the bottom of the <hi>Sinus</hi> whence the bloud came, and cramming the whole Cavity with the like, dipt in <hi>Poſca,</hi> to make the better preſſure: I bound her up as well as I could, and ſo left her; ſhe bled not afterward, but died in ſix or ſeven weeks of the <hi>Cancer,</hi> which ſhe would not by any perſwaſion be prevailed on to have extirpated.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="observation">
               <head>
                  <hi>Obſervation</hi> IX.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anno</hi> 76. A young Man about twenty years old, living with <hi>Alderman W.</hi> (whoſe Nephew he was) from ſome diſappoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in Love, as was imagined, or rather as himſelf confeſſed, on a Religious ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count, to cure ſalacious heats, did caſtrate himſelf, by griping up the <hi>Teſticles,</hi> with the whole <hi>Scrotum</hi> in one hand, and with a keen Knife in the other cutting them off cloſe to the body; the ſudden pain and effuſion of bloud made him faint and fall back on the Bed, where he ſat while he thus acted <hi>Origen Secundus.</hi> He bled very largely before any one diſcovered it: when I came, finding ſuch a large flux, and the
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:106833:53"/>man much weakned, I haſtily griped up the Wound in my hand, thereby ſtopping the exceſs of the <hi>Hemorrhage;</hi> while <hi>Mr. Munyon</hi> prepared the Dreſſings: when they were ready, withdrawing my hand to make way for their application, the bloud forth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with ſpouted out, as it had been from a ſmall Quill: but we ſoon ſtopped it, by laying on the divided <hi>Vaſa</hi> buttons of Tow dipt in the hot Oil of <hi>Terebinth;</hi> and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver all a large Pledget dipt in the ſame: over which alſo we put two or three Pled<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gets more armed with the common Defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſative and boulſters of Linnen, moiſtned with <hi>Poſca,</hi> and ſo rouled him up: the bloud inſtantly ſtaunched, but the refracti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on thereof threw him into a <hi>Syncope,</hi> toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with coldneſs of the extream parts, no pulſe, &amp;c. I concluded Death would fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low; we gave him a glaſs of Sack while the following mixture was preparing, of which he afterwards drank liberally, till his ſpirits were recovered to a good degree; ℞ <hi>Aq. Mirabilis, Flor. paralyſios, Meliſſae, Ceraſor. nigr. an</hi> ℥iij. <hi>Syr. Croci optimi</hi> ℥ij. <hi>Conf. Alkermes S. M.</hi> 
                  <g ref="char:dram">ʒ</g>iij, <hi>Spec. conf. Hyacinth.</hi> 
                  <g ref="char:dram">ʒ</g>j. <hi>Pulv. guttatae</hi> ℈ij. <hi>miſce.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>We opened the Wound next day, found tokens of good digeſtion, and as fair as heart could wiſh. It was long e're he could
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:106833:54"/>recruit his ſpirits, ſo much exhauſted by the <hi>Hemorrhage;</hi> but the Wound in a months time was almoſt cicatrized, ſo as he followed his buſineſs.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="observation">
               <head>
                  <hi>Obſervation</hi> X.</head>
               <p>A Seaman came to me, who having by accident thruſt the point of a Knife deep into his hand, between the <hi>Corpus</hi> and the Contracter of the Thumb, an Artery being thereby wounded, the bloud ſpout<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed out very impetuouſly; heating ſome <hi>Ol. Terebinthinae</hi> in my <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>vula ſpoon,</hi> I poured it into the bleeding Wound, which imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately ſtopped it; I only laid a <hi>Paracel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus</hi> and <hi>Diapalma</hi> Plaiſter over it, and bound him, and ſo let him remain two days, in which time it was perfectly cloſed.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="observation">
               <head>
                  <hi>Obſervation</hi> XI.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>A Cooper,</hi> ſtriking hard with his Addis on the Chime-hoop of an Hogſhead, ſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing an end, and miſſing the place where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>at the blow was deſigned, the Tool flew out of his hand and hit him croſs the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtep or <hi>Tarſus,</hi> making a large Wound, di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viding the Veins, &amp;c. to the bone, he bled very much, he was a thin man, and of
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:106833:54"/>hot ſharp bloud; I dreſſed him with hot <hi>Ol. Terebinth,</hi> which reſtraining the flux, gave me opportunity to ſtitch up the wound: ſome little veſications occurred by the Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cine meeting ſuch a habit; but it begat no trouble at all.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="observation">
               <head>
                  <hi>Obſervation</hi> XII.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>John Boddam,</hi> belonging to Captain <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trick of Yarmouth,</hi> ſtanding in the coyle of an Halcer, by which the Ship was faſtned: the ſtraps that tied it giving way, he was drawn forward, and griped therein: ſo that both Legs were ſhattered in pieces, he was brought to ſhore and committed to my cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtody. I reduced all the bones as well as could be, but when the contuſed fleſh came away, one of them hung by a Ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don or two above the Ancle. In fine, an Amputation was inevitable; he was a flo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rid young Man, and of a replete Habit, though ſome of it had been rebated by the method of <hi>Phlebotomy,</hi> &amp;c. uſed at firſt: after the member was ſevered at the uſual place, I only laid on a large Pledget of Tow, dipt in hot <hi>Ol. Terebinth,</hi> and the other things as is uſual, whereby the flux was ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denly and ſafely ſecured.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="observation">
               <pb n="80" facs="tcp:106833:55"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>Obſervation</hi> XIII.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anno 77. Captain P. Piper, the only Son of the Honourable Sir Hugh Piper, Deputy Governour of his Majeſties Cittadel of Pli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mouth;</hi> a man of a temper abounding with Choller, aduſt humours: his bloud ſharp and thin, received a large contuſed wound on the forepart of his Head, dividing ſome branches of the temporal Artery, contu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing the frontal and temporal Muſcles: he bled much, which was ſtopped by <hi>Mr. I. I.</hi> a great deal of pain, <hi>Spaſmus Cynicus,</hi> and Fever followed it; a Phyſician was cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, <hi>Phlebotomy, Clyſters, Julaps, Emulſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,</hi> &amp;c. had been uſed for nine days, and an Incarnative Dreſs too; when on a ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den, and without any manifeſt cauſe, the bloud ruſhed out from the Wound under the Dreſſings very copiouſly. I was haſtily called, and cut off the Rowlers, laying the Wound bare, did attempt with my Fingers to choke the bleeding <hi>Arteries</hi> while my Medicine was heating: the Gentleman be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan to faint; I encouraged him, and dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted him to keep his Eyes cloſe ſhut, that none of my Medicines might get into them and pain him. He ſat up whilſt I laid two Doſſils dipt in hot <hi>Oleum Terebinthinae</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:106833:55"/>the Wound and bound him up, the bloud immediately ſtaunched; but ſome of the Oil ſtealing into his Eye, begat great pain therein, which we endeavoured to mitigate, by often waſhing it with Spawn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>water, Milk, whites of Eggs, &amp;c. but in vain; for in deſpight thereof, it con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued two hours, and then began to range to his Wound, as ſeverely as at firſt to his Eye. I freely conſented to remove my Dreſſings, that the Wound might be examined. Accordingly the Head was unrouled, and all taken off, ſave only the two Doſſils, which we al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo were about to remove. When he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired us to forbear, for that his pain was gone. Upon which conſideration we let him lie, and applying over them a mix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of <hi>Bole,</hi> &amp;c. rouled him up again very ſlack; but no ſooner was the Head covered again with the bandage, but the pain returned as ſharp as before. We thereupon adminiſtred a Clyſter; in the working of which he fainted: when he was recovered thereof, he became very fearful and impatient. I propoſed the gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving him an ounce of <hi>Syr. de Meconio,</hi> they were unwilling for fear of prejudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing his Nerves: at length we agreed to give half an ounce in a Cephalick Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lap;
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:106833:56"/>
                  <hi>Ex Aq. Ceraſor. Nigr. Flor. Paralyſ. Jugland. S. Peoniae. Marguerit. V. Pp.</hi> &amp;c. which in leſs than a quarter of an hour made him ſleep, in which he continued ſome hours; upon his waking, he found himſelf quit of all pain, which induced us to forbear removing his Dreſs, till compleat thirty hours after its applicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: at which time I took it off, in pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of the Doctor and <hi>Mr. I.</hi> who firſt dreſſed him; both whom can teſtifie, that the wound was neither inflamed, red, bliſter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, nor crude, but of a lovely white, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving in it a little, but very good matter.</p>
               <p>I cannot imagine what ſhould cauſe this pain in the Wound, except the heat of my Application accending the bili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous particles of the bloud about the Wound, made them heat and prick the <hi>Pericranium, frontal Muſcles,</hi> &amp;c. but why then no ill effect ſhould appear in the Wound, is to me very ſtrange; as alſo that upon taking off the Rouler, the pain ſhould vaniſh, and return upon its being re-applyed; he was very impatient, and every one knoweth, that to ſuch, ſmall things are a greater burthen, than weighty ones to a pacifique temper. There was one action did very much ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifie me, and ſatisfie them: which was,
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:106833:56"/>that <hi>Sir Hugh Piper</hi> himſelf, when run through the Thigh by a broad two-edg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Sword, which wounding ſome of the crural Veſſels, begat a monſtrous flux; had this Medicine injected very hot into the Wound, and there retained by the hands of a Chirurgeon, till it had ſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red the <hi>Hemorrhage;</hi> after which, Tents dipt in the ſame were applyed alſo: I ſay, that the proſperous effects of that Application, both in reſtraining a flux of bloud, which would have killed a man of his Age, which had not his courage, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides the other benefits it procured the VVound, quieted him very much, who would otherwiſe have been tempted to believe upon the ſuggeſtions of a very in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidious Perſon familiar with him, that ſome inartificial application had begot all this trouble; but he recovered, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came very ſenſible, that I ſaved his life.</p>
               <p>If this Accident ſeem to diſparage our Medicine, or be an Objection againſt it, on account of its heat; it's but to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider, whether if in this very caſe I had uſed a Cautery, or Corroſive, to which (they being the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ltimum Refugium</hi>) I might have been tempted, on ſuch an extremity, I had not in all likelihood provoked worſe ſymptoms from their
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:106833:57"/>much greater heat, which would have kindled the humour into a ſtronger flame, and perhaps (though he had been ſo much bleeded) have begotten a Frenzy.</p>
               <p>Sir, It were endleſs to enlarge upon this matter; I ſuppoſe here is enough ſaid to ſatisfie every Artiſt; if they are not perſuaded hereby, let them experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment the thing, and if it anſwers not all I have ſaid of it, they will not be ſo fortunate as my ſelf. I am ſure I have been very faithful in the relation of fact; how defective in the Theory, I muſt leave to the judgment of every ingenious Reader.</p>
               <p>And now, Sir, having ſhewed you the bulk of the beſt Treaſure in this Cabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>net; bleſs me with your patience, while I take notice of the more obvious, and leſs conſiderable Riches it contains; I mean the more common and known Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues of this celebrated Oil, and thoſe I diſtinguiſh into two Heads: thoſe purchaſed by external Applications, and thoſe by inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Adminiſtrations.</p>
               <p>Our Diſcourſe hitherto having conſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed wholly of the former:<note place="margin">The Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues of <hi>O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leum Tereb.</hi> external<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly uſed.</note> I deem it moſt methodical to continue it, by ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king notice of that ſort firſt. I have al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:106833:57"/>manifeſted, that it reſtrains <hi>Hemor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rhagies,</hi> quickens Digeſtion, conſolidates, reſtrains the extravagant profluence of the <hi>Serum,</hi> whether from the Joints, Nerves, <hi>Lympheducts,</hi> or Sanguiferous Veſſels: cures Punctures, and all wounds of the Nerves, and is an excellent Balſam againſt any hurt to them: its other external Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues are, (with reſpect to VVounds above what hath been ſaid,) that it warms and comforts thoſe, wherein from any cauſe the ſpirits and native heat is deſtroyed, or impaired; it acuates the digeſtive quality of any Medicine; recovers Cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dity, Palſey, Convulſion, &amp;c. of a Wound; it moderately incarneth, and doth not a little Cicatrize, as is evident from its cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring chaps of the Lips, Breaſt, and Fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dament, or any excoriation without heat, and from whence much <hi>Serum</hi> floweth; it's celebrated for producing fair Cica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trixes, and mending deformed ones: to both which purpoſes, it's uſed after the ſmall Pox; as <hi>Euonymus Philiatrus</hi> in his <hi>Theſaurus</hi> commends, from <hi>Braſavolus,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Page 316.</note> as a great Secret.</p>
               <p>It cruſts up Sloughs, whether <hi>fungous,</hi> or grangrenous, Cadaver, and ſometimes not only uſed hot with Pledgets, but mixed with <hi>Lixiviums;</hi> by which alſo it
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:106833:58"/>quickens, comforts and ſtrengthens any part, paralytick, mortified, oedematous, &amp;c. for it warms, and attenuates, whereby the afflux of the animal ſpirits is accelerated; it alſo opens,<note place="margin">Paracelſ. chyr. mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na, <hi>tract. 3. c. 7.</hi> Beguinus Tyro. chym. <hi>lib. 2. c. 6.</hi>
                  </note> diſcuſſeth, ſoftens, &amp;c. cureth malignant and ſordid Ulcers, <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coethe ulcera, phagadena lupus,</hi> is a good Liniment in Contuſions, being mixed with <hi>Oleum Hypericonis.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>One drachm thereof, mixed with <hi>Ax<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ungia Porcina,</hi> is a moſt admirable Oint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment for cold ſwellings and ſtiffneſs of the Joints, Muſcles, or Sinews, from the Scurvy, Cold, or Obſtructions. It bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters the penetration of any Liniment wherewith it's commixed, making it alſo more warming and ſtrengthening; it's A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nodyne to Tumours that are painful from Cold; it's an excellent Liniment, either u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed by its ſelf, or with other ſtrengtheners, to cure <hi>Atrophies.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It acuates the balſamick quality of any Salve, being it ſelf a true Balſam. <hi>James Cook</hi> giveth us an Oil (which he ſtole from <hi>Hartman</hi> and <hi>Erneſtus</hi>) <hi>quod vulnera in</hi> 24 <hi>horas ſanat &amp; eſt expertum.</hi> ℞ <hi>Ol. Hypericonis, Lumbricorum, Terebinthinae, Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtich. ana p. e. Miſce &amp; calide cum pauco goſſypio applica;</hi> Oil of <hi>Terebinth</hi> alſo diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolveth hard ſwellings, proceeding from a
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:106833:58"/>cold cauſe, is excellent being dropped warm into the Ears alone, or commixed, to cure deafneſs, or noiſe therein, from cold obſtructions, &amp;c. it alſo cleanſeth, or healeth Ulcers therein.</p>
               <p>It's excellent to anoint parts contracted, nummed, crampt, convulſt, paralytick, cold, gouty, pains, eſpecially the <hi>Sciatica:</hi> in all which effects, a Medicine of <hi>Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>celſus,</hi> called <hi>Balſamum Galbanatum,</hi> and made of a ſolution of <hi>Galbanum</hi> in this Oil, and ſo drawn over the Helm, is a moſt admirable Secret, which I would com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend to the practice of the Sea-Chirur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geon; whereas he ſhall find it a moſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent, (being alſo a cheap) Medicine, either uſed alone, or as I do, mixed with double, treble, quadruple, ſometimes ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times its quantity of any proper Oil or Oint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: Such are <hi>Ol. Caſtorei, Catulorum, Lum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bricor. <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nguent. Martiatum, Cervinum,</hi> &amp;c. as need ſhall require. I have cured con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracted members thereby in a little time, and have ſeen wonderful good effects pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced by it in the <hi>Pareſis</hi> of the Limbs, following bilious and ſcorbutick <hi>Colicks.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Being put hot into hollow Teeth, it aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwageth their pain, eſpecially if therein a little <hi>Opium,</hi> or <hi>Camphor.</hi> be diſſolved;<note place="margin">The in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal vertues of <hi>Ol. Tere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>binth.</hi>
                  </note> as to the Vertues thereof, when adminiſtred
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:106833:59"/>internally, It opens the Urinary paſſages, tempers their heat, prevents and cureth the Stone, cleanſeth the Reins and Lungs from any tartarous mucilages; cures the <hi>Gonorrhea,</hi> cleanſeth the generative parts from venerious impurities: is excellent in the <hi>Strangury, Dyſuria, Iſchuria,</hi> brings off Gravel and calculous matter; cureth Ul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers in the Reins and Bladder, pain in the Back, poceeding from any of the ſaid cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, or from Cold; cureth piſſing of bloud, taken in juice of Yarrow, Nettles, or Plan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain.</p>
               <p>It cureth Coughs, taken in Scabious, Colts-foot, or Hyſop-water; cleanſeth the Breaſt and Lungs, taken in Ptyſan or pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctoral Decoction; cureth Ulcers there ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken in Conſerve of Roſes, Camphory, or Ground-Ivy, or drunk in equal parts of <hi>Aq. Veronicae, Hedera terreſt. &amp; Aq. Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cis:</hi> ſweetned with <hi>Syr. Piloſellae,</hi> quickens expectoration of matter, taken in pectoral Decoction, ſweetned with <hi>Oxymel of Squils,</hi> or <hi>Syr. de Eryſimo,</hi> cureth the <hi>Phthiſis,</hi> mixed with the Conſerve of Roſes, and all (eſpecially cold) afflictions of the Breaſt; it openeth, warmeth, and comforteth ner<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vous parts,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>See</hi> Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thew's Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>learned Alchymiſt, <hi>page 27.</hi>
                  </note> taken in a proper Vehicle, as the caſe may require; it is an excellent corrector of <hi>Opium;</hi> it cureth internal Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuſions,
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:106833:59"/>given in Spruce-beer, Carduus-water, or <hi>Aq. Polygoni,</hi> conſolidates internal Wounds and Ulcers, eſpecially of the Breaſt, where it not only healeth the parts, but deriveth and evacuates the matter by Urine, being given in vulnerary Drinks, &amp;c. It cleanſeth the ſtomach of viſcous, ſordid, filthy mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, taken with <hi>Aq. Menthae, Centauriae, aut Abſinthij, vel vino Albo:</hi> it warms the ſemi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal parts, <hi>&amp; libidini ſtimulos addit;</hi> it cleanſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the Womb, and cureth Uterine ſuffoca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, taken in <hi>Aq. Naphae, Aq. Artemiſiae, De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coctum ſplene bovis, Querc.</hi> it openeth the Spleen, taken in Tamarisk, Ceterach, Aſh, Harts-tongue, Heath, or Smallage-water; re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſteth peſtilential malignity, taken in ſome proper <hi>Alexiterial</hi> Medicine.</p>
               <p>Though the <hi>Gonorrhoea,</hi> being uſually ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>companied with heat in thoſe parts, ſeems a Diſeaſe more aptly aggravated, than reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>died by this Medicine; yet it, by carrying off thoſe fiery particles, and cleanſing the parts from that venene matter, which is the <hi>pabulum,</hi> and inflames; takes the heat alſo (which is its effect) away: ſtopping alſo the flux, by healing the vellications of the <hi>Proſtata,</hi> which cauſeth that weeping, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly ſuppoſed, and denominated a flux of the <hi>Sperm,</hi> and running of the Reins.</p>
               <p>In all which caſes, its doſe is from <hi>Gut.
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:106833:60"/>V. ad</hi> ℈ j. <hi>&amp;</hi> 
                  <g ref="char:dram">ʒ</g> ſs. always taken in a pertinent Vehicle, never alone: all thoſe additional vertues which I have here adſcribed to the Medicine, have been the ſuggeſtions of the following Authors, my own Reaſon and Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiology, and for the moſt part confirmed to me by experience: The Authors wherein all, or moſt I have ſaid, may be found, are, <hi>J. Beguinus</hi> in his <hi>Tyrocinium Chymicum, cum notis J. Barthii. &amp; J. G. Pelſhoferi, lib.</hi> 2. <hi>cap.</hi> 4, <hi>&amp;</hi> 6. <hi>J. Erneſtus de oleis Chymice deſtilla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis,</hi> page 434. <hi>M. Le Febure, part.</hi> 2. <hi>lib.</hi> 2. <hi>cap.</hi> 9. <hi>ſect.</hi> 10. <hi>M. Charras pharmacopoea</hi> 11. <hi>R. Galenique, &amp; Chymique, part</hi> 3. <hi>lib.</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi> 42 <hi>Mr. Woodal, Zwelfer,</hi> and the <hi>Auguſtanes, Mant. Hermetica, Euonymus Philiatrus, deremediis ſecretis, page</hi> 316. <hi>Paracelſus Chirurgia Mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na, tract.</hi> 2. <hi>c.</hi> 4. <hi>&amp; tract.</hi> 3. <hi>c.</hi> 7. <hi>M. C. Glaſſier</hi> in his <hi>Compleat Chymiſt, lib.</hi> 2. <hi>ſect.</hi> 2. <hi>cap.</hi> 7.</p>
               <p>And now, Sir, This occaſion would tempt one that underſtands ſo well as I do, the great kindneſſes you have done the Practiſers of our Art, in an age wherein they are ſo much contemned and diſparaged; to Careſs and Complement you for that Obligation: but I will not offer that affront to your mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty, nor can I imagine it needful here, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the publick military Chirurgeons, are the perſons for whom it's deſigned, who
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:106833:60"/>having had all of them the ſenſible benefit thereof, as well as my ſelf, cannot be want<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in their reſentments of thoſe advantages you have ſo generouſly and candidly pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cured them, as I am a participater of the latter; I'le aſſure you the former hath very ſtrictly bound me, ever to be your moſt af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectionate, and grateful, as I am,</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Your very much obliged Servant, <hi>James Young.</hi>
                  </signed>
                  <dateline>
                     <hi>Plim.</hi> 
                     <date>
                        <hi>April</hi> 8. 1678.</date>
                  </dateline>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="postscript">
               <head>POSTSCRIPT.</head>
               <p>SINCE my finiſhing theſe Papers, I have met with a paſſage in <hi>Mr. Serjeant Wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man's Book, page</hi> 359. which ſeeming to op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe and deny ſome of thoſe Vertues I have here attributed to <hi>Ol. Terebinth,</hi> obligeth me to take notice thereof, and to juſtifie what I have affirmed, contrary to what he there delivereth in the Hiſtory of a Maids caſe; <hi>Who,</hi> ſaith he, <q rend="inline">
                     <hi>by a young Chirurge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons attempting to bleed her in the Saphena near the Ancle, had a puncture of a tendon there, which was dreſſed with hot Oil of Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rebinth; her pain thereupon increaſing, I was called, and found the Chirurgeon about to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>new
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:106833:61"/>the application of his hot Oils: but ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerving the lips of the Wound turgid and dry, and the parts about it inflamed, I pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vailed with him to dreſs with warm Baſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licon, to embrocate</hi> cum Ol. Roſar. &amp;c. <hi>and apply a Diapalma Plaiſter malaxed over all, and let is ſo abide three days: in which time it became well.</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>The implication is ſtrong againſt the uſe of <hi>Oleum Terebinthinae,</hi> as if it had made the Wound turgid, and dry, and inflamed the part: the firſt and laſt are known uſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally to follow punctures of the Tendons: and yet even where they urge, <hi>Johannes de Vigo,</hi> and <hi>A. Pareus</hi> do eſpecially, direct to the uſe of ſcalding hot Oils and Cauteries. Now as to this caſe in particular, if it were a punctured Tendon, the <hi>Oleum Terebin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thinae</hi> had healed it (as appeared by its dri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs) and prevented the common and moſt pernicious accidents, as Convulſions, Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traction, &amp;c. which would without doubt have ſeized her without it, and that thoſe mentioned were cured by the after-appli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, for I never heard of any cured by the abſolute uſe of Anodynes: or one ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication of a ſlight Digeſtive, as by his ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice was here applyed; but as he had be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore generally directed, by applications hot, and dry, and of ſubtil parts, (though there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:106833:61"/>Anodynes to prevent accidents are very neceſſary) in which all Authors treat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thereof, ſeem to concur: Such are <hi>Ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len,</hi> lib. 6. with c. 2. <hi>Avicen,</hi> lib. 3. c. 4. <hi>Vigo,</hi> lib. 3. c. 15. <hi>Guido,</hi> in lib. 3. <hi>Gal. Pareus,</hi> lib. 10. c. 38. <hi>P. Pigreus,</hi> lib. 3. <hi>de Vuln.</hi> c. 5. <hi>P. Barbet.</hi> c. 8. p. 2. <hi>Mr. Banniſter,</hi> lib. 2. c. 10. <hi>Dr. A. Read, Lect.</hi> 2. <hi>F. Sylvius, nov. Idea, part</hi> 1. c. 42. <hi>Mr. Clows obſ.</hi> c. 10. as is alſo evident in the method of <hi>P. Fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtus,</hi> lib. 6. <hi>obſ. chyr. obſ.</hi> 38. <hi>Scultetus, obſ.</hi> 64. All which are according <hi>Mr. Wiſeman's</hi> excellent Direction, hot, dry, and ſubtil; ſuch are <hi>Aq. Vitae, Ol. Terebinth, Ol. Euphorh. Ol. Sabinum, Caſtorei, Pulegii,</hi> Powder, Plai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, and tincture of <hi>Euphorhium, rectified ſpirit of Wine,</hi> &amp;c. all to have an actual heat added to their potential, eſpecially when the pain increaſeth, and the lips ſwell; ſo that I may rationally preſume to doubt, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the wounded Tendon were not cured, and the uſual ſymptoms attending them pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vented by the firſt Dreſs; and whether a reflection on the neglect of cojuvant Ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dynes, had not been more juſt and rational, ſince <hi>de facto</hi> it appeared, they only (and not much neither) were wanting to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleat the work, by removing thoſe leſſer ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cidents, which might be the effect of the Patients ill habit, moſt Women, needing
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:106833:62"/>Phlebotomy, there being ſo, elſe it becomes doubtful, whether any Tendon was punctu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, except there were more pertinent ſym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptomes to prove it, than the Serjeant was pleaſed to relate. This I am tempted to ſcruple alſo, from its being cured by one pledget of <hi>Baſilicon,</hi> and a mildly Anodyne Plaiſter; which doubtleſs, as it could not without a Miracle heal a punctured Nerve; ſo it is a moſt incomparable way of remedy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thoſe ill effects, the conſequents of feſter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing punctures, in ill Habits; the <hi>Baſilicon</hi> digeſting, and diſcharging the matter, while the Plaiſter and Liniment prevented and cured the pain, heat, and conflux, which would otherwiſe beget worſe effects.</p>
               <p>How frequently Women that need <hi>Phlebo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tomy</hi> in thoſe parts are either <hi>Cachectick,</hi> ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructed, or phlethorick, needs no proof, nor how incident ſuch habits are, to have ſevere ſymptomes follow; not only regular and well-performed <hi>Phlebotomy,</hi> as <hi>Mr. Wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi> hath well hinted, but even ſmall pun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctures of Pins, Fiſh-bones, Needles, or the like, where no Tendon or Nerve hath been touched; as hath been evident from the ſymptomes which have had no relation to them, or their kind: but have apparently been produced by that blood and matter, (eſpecially if a Veſſel be hurt) that hath
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:106833:62"/>been extravaſate into the inconſpicuous Wound, which being either very menſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, as in Women, or venereal, as in ſome Men, or ſharp, &amp;c. as in moſt others: hath for want of vent diffuſed among the tender ſenſible parts, gnawing and corrupting them, which (as all pains do) alſo attracting, and heaping up matter: and as ſoon debauch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it, gangrenates, or at beſt rots the part, ſo much as in ſome, to coſt the member. This I have again and again ſeen to ſucceed pun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctures in the Fingers, for want of timely Art.</p>
               <p>That exquiſite ſymptomes have been the effects of ſlight ſimple punctures, meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing an ill habit, is the poſitive averment of <hi>Galen;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Lib. 3. Method. <hi>Obſerv.</hi> 5.</note> of which alſo there is a notable in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance in <hi>Mr. Grand Prez,</hi> which though he calls the puncture of a Nerve made by a Needle, was doubtleſs no ſuch thing; <hi>firſt,</hi> becauſe he had no pain in two days, which were impoſſible in a puncture of a Nerve or Tendon; <hi>ſecondly,</hi> becauſe it ſubmitted on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to an antivenerial ſuffumigation of the part, which he was induced to make uſe of, becauſe he had been lately pockt; and that all the commonly practiſed ways had no good effect.</p>
               <p>And <hi>Mr. Wiſeman</hi> himſelf excellently well obſerveth, that after <hi>Phlebotomy,</hi> ſevere ſym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptomes
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:106833:63"/>do ſometimes ariſe on the part bleed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, which though they are not from a pun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture, yet the vulgar, and the envious uſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally ſo apprehended them. I know a very good Chirurgeon who had an <hi>Eryſipelas</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vade an Arm, he had bleeded, the which to revel, and derive, he opened a Vein in the other alſo, which became thereupon af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted, as its fellow-member was: both which he cured by purging and diet, which plainly demonſtrated that there was no pun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture, though the people to his great da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage would not ſo underſtand it.</p>
               <p>I never had the misfortune of puncturing a Nerve or Tendon once, nor the unhappi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of the imputation more than twice: the one was of a young cholerick Man, who ſitting all the following night at Dice, (which he managed with the hand I had bleeded) had the part apoſtumate over the <hi>median Vein;</hi> in which place he being thin, and impatient, it made ſevere ſymptomes: my abſence induced him to apply himſelf to one, who miſtaking it for a puncture, drop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped upon it hot Oil of <hi>Terebinth,</hi> and laid on a <hi>Paracelſus</hi> Plaiſter, which ſo accended the humours in the part, already inflamed with a beginning <hi>Phlegmon,</hi> that he could not indure it; by which time I being re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned, laid on an Anodyne and mildly ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>purative
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:106833:63"/>Cataplaſm, a ſmall pledget armed with <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nguent. Baſilicon,</hi> being firſt applyed to the Wound, which ſoon opened it, and diſcharged the matter to his great eaſe. I inlarged the Orifice, and gave it more libe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral vent, upon which it ſoon healed up.</p>
               <p>The other was a perſon of Worſhip, Sir <hi>B. G.</hi> the Engineer, who labouring under an intermitting Fever, (as I take it) was by <hi>Dr. Sprages</hi> order bleeded by me, after which I ſaw him not in three weeks, and then found him among the Workmen at the Cittadel, where he told me all was well, ſave ſome Colical pains, which had lately ſeized him. Soon after this he journeyed to <hi>London;</hi> about ſix weeks after the operati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, his Worſhip's Arm began to pain him, and impoſtumate; it was my ill luck, that he fell into the hands of ſome Chirurgeon in <hi>London;</hi> no leſs envious, than ignorant; who affirmed it to proceed from my inarti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficial <hi>Phlebotomy,</hi> made ſo long before, and (which was a great Miracle) that I had prickt a Nerve: this ſo inraged the Knight, as made me bleſs my ſelf, I was beyond the reach of his Swords point: I laboured to ſatisfie him with (what is not always pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>valent) <hi>Reaſon;</hi> and did earneſtly impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune him, to give me the name of that good man my Accuſer, which though a moſt reaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:106833:64"/>Suit, was yet denied, and to this day I know him not; but if this Paper ever fall into his hands, and if he have any ſenſe of generoſity in him, it will oblige him to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quit, or juſtifie himſelf.</p>
               <p>He might have affirmed innocently e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough, that my bleeding him had occaſion<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed this accident; had he aſſigned the true Reaſon, not the puncture of a Tendon, as he ridiculouſly did: but as I am induced to believe, that it was the remains of the <hi>Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brile Pabulum:</hi> part of which, having been before diſcharged that way, and now mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved by a <hi>critical Fermentation</hi> was come to ſeek vent, (or rather Nature endeavoured to eject it) the ſame place: but miſſing it, did there depoſit it, and begat that apoſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation. which in a part ſo tender, from the complication of many Veſſels, and a perſon not leſs ſo, from his long ſickneſs and cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lerick habit, might beget ſharp and violent ſymptoms, reſembling thoſe of a Puncture; differing herein, that all ſuch are ſudden as well as violent, and do ſoon affect the whole <hi>nervous genus</hi> with <hi>Convulſions, Spaſms, Contractions,</hi> &amp;c. as the late quoted Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors do all aver, and the following notable Caſe, notoriouſly manifeſts.</p>
               <p>A Woman aged about twenty five years, living with <hi>Mr. B.</hi> His Majeſties Surveyer in
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:106833:64"/>this Port, being of an Habit replete with ill Juices, and full of other effects, reſulting from Uterine obſtructions, was punctured by an Apothecary attempting to open the <hi>median Vein,</hi> in the great Tendon under it: intolerable pain, contraction, and tumor immediately ſeized the part, together with faintneſs, &amp;c. though the unhappy bleeder had given her a draught of ſome hot Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dial-water to prevent it. The accidents gaining conſiderably and encreaſing upon her; he was ſent for, and though it were very apparent from the great and ſudden inflammation, tumour, contraction, and ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible tendency to Convulſions, that the Ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don was prickt; yet he affirmed it was no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing extraordinary, nor more than would be ſoon cured, by anointing the part with ſome Oil of Elder, and Roſe-flowers: they unhappily believed it, and relied on that one Medicine till the next day; at which time, the ſymptomes were become ſo vehe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and threatening, that they called me. I immediately aſſured them of the reaſon and danger of all thoſe accidents, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>took my ſelf to remedy what I could of them, and prevent the ſurvening of worſe, which I ſaw at hand; whilſt I ordered ſome topical application, my Servant bled her at the oppoſite arm, and drew ten or twelve
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:106833:65"/>ounces: by which time my Medicines being ready, I dilated the Orifice, and poured in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to it <hi>equal parts of rectified ſpirit of Wine, and Oleum Terebinthinae,</hi> made very hot, and upon it a Pledget of <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nguent. Baſilicon,</hi> em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brocating the member with this Liniment; ℞ <hi>Ol. Roſarum, Catellorum, an.</hi> ℥ j. <hi>Balſ. Gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>banati</hi> 
                  <g ref="char:dram">ʒ</g> j. <hi>miſce.</hi> and ſo wrapped it in Lin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nen, dipt in <hi>Poſca,</hi> and rouled it up from the <hi>Carpus</hi> to the ſhoulder: I alſo ordered a ſharp Clyſter to be adminiſtred, and the following Julaps, and Powders to be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared; ℞ <hi>Aq. Naphae, Ceraſor. Nigr. ana</hi> ℥iij. <hi>Lumbricorum Mag. Brion. Comp. Peon. C. Syr. Artemiſiae, Peoniae. S. ana</hi> ℥iſs. <hi>Tinct. Succini Caſtor. ana</hi> 
                  <g ref="char:dram">ʒ</g> j. <hi>miſce.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>℞ <hi>Pulv. Guttatae. S. M.</hi> 
                  <g ref="char:dram">ʒ</g> j. <hi>Marg. verij. p. p. Sal. Succini ana</hi> ℈ j. <hi>m. f. chart.</hi> 4. <hi>un. quart. qua<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> hor. ſumend. c. hauſtulo praedicti Julapi.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But e're theſe things could be given, her pain, inflamation encreaſed, and threw her into frequent Convulſions: I repeated my Dreſs to the Wound, and wrapped the arm in an Anodyne Cataplaſm, <hi>ex lacte, mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cae panis Alb. Florum, Sambuci, Roſarum, Croci &amp; <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nguent. populei;</hi> appointing a temperate Dyet, <hi>viz.</hi> Grewel for meat; and for drink, <hi>a ptyſan of Barley, Liquorice, Rad. Peoniae. flor. Peoniae. Tamarinda, cocted, and
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:106833:65"/>made pleaſant with Syrup of ſingle Peony Flowers.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The next morning, I found the contraction of the arm increaſed, the Convulſions had come oftner, and <hi>Lipothymia</hi> more frequent, which had almoſt induced me to divide the punctured Tendon, but I determined yet to forbear; and repeating the Clyſter, I em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brocated the Neck-bone down the Spine, ſhoulder, over the <hi>Biceps, Deltoides,</hi> and <hi>Brachicus muſculus,</hi> &amp;c. eſpecially, with the aforeſaid Liniment: towards noon, finding no abatement, and my Patient in imminent danger of life, led by what reſolution I know not, I ſtill reſolved to forbear the cutting aſunder of the Tendon; and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtead thereof, I ſcarified all the forepart of the arm, from the ſhoulder to the <hi>Carpus,</hi> eſpecially over the muſcles above-named, and about the Puncture, from which iſſued a thin bloud in great abundance, even to a pound: I made one deep cut over the Ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don, according to his length, making him bare almoſt an inch, into which I poured my mixture of ſpirit of Wine and Oil of <hi>Terebinth,</hi> made very warm, and bound up the arm with Ligature, &amp;c. as at the firſt, and continued all the other Medicines; by the next Dreſſing, which was at night, I prepared this Fomentation.</p>
               <pb n="102" facs="tcp:106833:66"/>
               <p>℞ <hi>Foliorum Paralyſios, cum Flor. Salviae, Betonicae, Hyper. ana</hi> m. iij. <hi>Laurini, Laven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dule, Roriſmarinae, Scordei, Rutae, ana</hi> m. i. s. <hi>Flor. Sambuci, Melliloti, ana</hi> m. j. <hi>Conciſ. &amp; coq. in conq.</hi> i. s. <hi>Aq. Fontanae, ad tertiae par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis abſumptionem, fiat Colat.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Wherewith I bathed the whole member for half an hour, deſigning thereby to ſtrengthen and eaſe the Nerves, diſcharge the Sanies from the punctured part, and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſs the matter, which the pain had plenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully contracted in ſo ill an Habit, and which threatned a Gangrene; and becauſe in many nights ſhe had not ſlept, and was ready to periſh for want of it, and eaſe, I ventured to give her this, ſlight <hi>Hypnotick:</hi> by whoſe mixture, you will ſee I endeavor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to prevent, and had regard to the miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chief it might do to the <hi>Genus Nervoſum,</hi> here ſo conſiderably aggrieved.</p>
               <p>℞ <hi>Aq. Jugland. S. Flor. Paralyſios, Papav. Rhead. ana</hi> 
                  <g ref="char:dram">ʒ</g> vj. <hi>Syr. de Meconio</hi> ℥ ſs. <hi>Spec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diambrae. ſ. m. Guttetae ſ. m. ana</hi> ℈ ſs. <hi>Tinct. Caſtorei, Laudan. Liquid. Helmonti, ana gut.</hi> 6. <hi>miſce.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And the better to ſecure the Brain from any prejudice thereby, I ordered a Clyſter to be adminiſtred half an hour before, and ſo left her; I was unquiet all night, in fear of her, the caſe being eſteemed deſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:106833:66"/>by all people, made me ſo anxious, for fear of miſſing the reputation I ſhould gain by ſo conſiderable a Cure, if I could effect it: I viſited her early, and no leſs to my joy than admiration, found ſhe had ſlept well all night, was in moderate temper without that ardor and thirſt, heart and pulſation, tumour, pain, or Convulſions, which had been ſo ſevere upon her; there ſeemed none of that legion of Devils that tormented her left, but the contraction and debility of the part, with the hardneſs and intumeſcence of the injured Tendon; there was reaſonable tendency to digeſtion, in all the inciſions I had made, excepting that over the Tendon, which was ſtill ſomewhat crude, and <hi>Ichorous:</hi> I ſomented the mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber as before, adding now a little ſpirit of Wine thereunto, and dreſſed the inciſion over the Puncture, with <hi>Baſilicon</hi> acuated with <hi>Oleum Terebinthinae,</hi> and both made warm; encompaſſing the member, in a cerat of <hi>Diapalma; Stict. Paracelſ. &amp; cera citrina, ana partes aequales,</hi> and ſo rouled it up. To be ſhort, from this time ſhe amended, in all reſpects, the ſcarifications ſoon healed, ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving that on the punctured Tendon, which being largeſt, and on the center of all the pain, &amp;c. was laſt cured, when nothing re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mained but the contraction of the member,
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:106833:67"/>and hardneſs of the ſinew, which however was not ſo much as before; hereupon I ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded ſome <hi>E. Oxicroceum</hi> to the Cerate, and framed the Liniment thus: ℞ <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nguent. Nervin. Martiat. Ol. Palmae, Ol. Catellorum, Caſtorei, ana</hi> ℥ j. <hi>Balſ. Galbanat.</hi> 
                  <g ref="char:dram">ʒ</g> iij. <hi>Ol. Succini,</hi> 
                  <g ref="char:dram">ʒ</g> ſs. <hi>m. fiat linimentum, S. A.</hi> By theſe in ſix or ſeven days time, the contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted Tendons and muſcles did manifeſtly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lax; ſo that her arm, though ſtill weak, was paſſively extenſible, above half its due lati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude. I now purged her, with <hi>Pill. Succino. Tartar. Quercetani, ana</hi> ℈ j. <hi>Reſinae Zallap: gr.</hi> viij. <hi>cum</hi> q. ſ. <hi>Balſ. Pemiviani p. Pill. 7. aurat.</hi> q. ſ. They wrought about eight motions, and ſeemed to have relieved her very much; from which time I left her to generals, and Dyet, continuing the Oint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, once in two days, which I directed to have chaffed well in, after the member had firſt been well ſoked in the reeking <hi>Viſcera,</hi> of a newly ſlain Beeſ; it was long e're ſhe could of her ſelf extend her arm fully, and ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what longer e're the ſtrength of it return<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed perfectly.</p>
               <p>It happened, (which I had forgot to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timate) that a few days after her purging, ſhe being returned towards evening from a walk ſhe had made to viſit ſome Friends in Town, fell into a ſevere Paroxyſm, convulſt,
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:106833:67"/>hyſterical, &amp;c. in which I thought ſhe would have died; I gave her a draught, &amp;c. which recovered her, after which it never return<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; I repeated the Pills, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>The prick of a Tendon, could ſcarcely have happened with more circumſtances, than it did here; for the pain thereof at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracted ſo powerfully the ill Juices, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with ſhe abounded, that ſhe was in equal hazard of Death, from their cauſing a Gan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grene, as from the convulſive effects of the Puncture: more ſevere and cruciating ſymp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toms I never ſaw in my life, in a body ſo unfit for them, and ſo unable to brook them: and certainly, had I delayed making that li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beral diſcharge, by the ſcarifications, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forting the part, and diſcuſſing the matter by the Fomentation, and allaying the fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentation of the bloud and humours by the Opiat, but that night, ſhe had been in her winding-ſheet, by the next; for the reſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the ſtrength, and extenſion of the mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, I own my ſelf indebted principally to the <hi>Balſamum Galb.</hi> of which I have al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready ſpoken ſo well.</p>
               <p>Sir, I will relieve your patience when I have related one Obſervation more of the effects of <hi>Oleum Terebinthinae,</hi> in an <hi>Hemor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rhage,</hi> happening by a Wound to a young Gentleman, <hi>Mr. A. Cock,</hi> Servant to an e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minent
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:106833:68"/>Merchant, and then Mayor of this Town, <hi>Mr. J. Lanyon,</hi> who whetting a long Penknife on a Hone, the Knife drop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping out of his Hand, fell towards the ground, between him and the wall of the Window, againſt which he ſtood: he in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſiderately thruſting his belly forward to ſtop it, and it unhappily falling with the point towards him, run up into the infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riour part of the left <hi>Ilia,</hi> from whence iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſued a great ſtream of Arterial bloud, which in a very ſmall ſpace had ran a great quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tity: I found him bleeding, in great pain, and very faint; I forthwith injected <hi>Oleum Terebinthinae,</hi> and thruſt in a large Tent, dip'd in the ſame, and bound him up, ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtring a Clyſter, by the working of which, I ſaw the <hi>Inteſtines</hi> were not hurt, as I feared; I continued my Tents armed with <hi>Linimentum Arcei,</hi> and put ſome Oil of <hi>Turpentine</hi> with the injection I uſed; the extravaſate bloud caſt into the hollow of the <hi>Abdomen,</hi> digeſted; and a Fever hapned while Nature was on that work, which I endeavoured not to check by any refrige<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rating courſe, but by drinking a decoction of ſome Vulneraries, with <hi>Crocus R. Glyz,</hi> &amp;c. and repeated Clyſters of the ſame: which haſtning the Coction, calmed the efferveſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cence of the bloud by conſequence; and ſo
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:106833:68"/>ſecurely was the hurt Artery cloſed, that not any recent bloud appeared after the firſt Dreſs, though the flagrancy of that Maſs made it hazardous. When I ſaw fair <hi>Pus,</hi> I put in a Fiſtula Tent, and diſchar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged it, and afterwards let it cloſe. I became induced to ſuperadd this Obſervation, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe in it the Medicine reſtrained ſo ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcure an <hi>Hemorrhage,</hi> though not made hot, for fear of injuring the Guts.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="108" facs="tcp:106833:69"/>
            <head>A new Way of Amputating large Members, and a more ſpeedy con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venient Method of curing Stumps, than that commonly practiſed.</head>
            <head type="sub">Diſcovered in a Letter, to his e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteemed Friend, Mr. <hi>THO. HOBS,</hi> Chirurgeon in <hi>London.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>Find by yours, that you are ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prized with the intimation I gave you, of a way of amputating large Members, ſo as to be able to cure them <hi>per Symphyſin,</hi> in three weeks, and without fouling, or ſcaling the bone. It is a Paradox that I will now evince to you to be a truth, after I have firſt taken notice of what you affirm, that there is a neceſſity of ſcaling the ends of thoſe bones, left bare after the uſual way of diſmembring, before the Stump can be ſoundly cured; that you never yet found it otherwiſe but that where
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:106833:69"/>it hath been attempted, the Stumps have apoſtumated, and the <hi>Caries</hi> come off thereby.</p>
            <p>Sir, I do aſſure you, I have been ſo happy to have ſeen the contrary, in an Amputation made between the <hi>Cubitus</hi> and the <hi>Carpus;</hi> where, though the Wound was almoſt nine weeks in curing, and at Sea too, yet the bones never ſcaled, and the ſtump remained (to my knowledg many months) without the leaſt tendency to eruption; the perſon then principally concerned was an old Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctitioner, and one that had long ſerved in the Northern Wars: he did aſſure me, he frequently neglected the ſcaling of the bone, and healed moſt of the Amputations he made in the Army, and in <hi>Scotland</hi> without it. I acquaint you of this for its rarity, not that I ever but once practiſed it, when I made Amputations the uſual way, and I think it not prudent, becauſe there is no ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity to imitate it in ſuch ſtumps: for that in curing them, we have time enough for the diſquamation, which is alſo atchieved with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any great trouble; whereas ſhould we neglect it, and ſind when the ſtumps come to be almoſt cicatrized (as once I did in deſigning to imitate the ſaid Artiſt, and which made me reſolve for ever to decline it) that there were neceſſity of doing it, by reaſon of a <hi>Caries</hi> then contracted, or but then diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covering
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:106833:70"/>it ſelf; it's manifeſt what trouble it would beget, and how greatly impede the deſiccation; there are thoſe that think they ought to ſcale all bones, that have though but by a recent Wound been bare: and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers I have met with who on the other hand too much ſlight the <hi>Caries</hi> of bones, pretend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing they moulder off with the matter; how equally unreaſonable and vain both are, I need not diſcourſe to ſo competent a Judg as your ſelf. Wherefore paſſing theſe mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, I ſhall now entertain you with an ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of the manner of this Operation, I would recommend to you, after I have told you, that it was from a very ingenious Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of ours, <hi>Mr. C. Lowdham of Exceter,</hi> that I had the firſt hints thereof.</p>
            <p>The Ligatures and Gripe, being made af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the common manner you are with your Catling, or ſome long inciſion-Knife, to raſe (ſuppoſe it the Leg) a flap of the membrane<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous fleſh, covering the muſcles of the Calf, beginning below the place where you intend to make exciſion, and raſing it thitherward, of length enough to cover the ſtump; ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving ſo done, turn it back under the hand of him that gripes: and as ſoon as you have ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered the member, bring this ſlap of Cutane<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous fleſh over the ſtump, and faſten it to the edges thereof, by four of five ſtrong ſtitches:
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:106833:70"/>having ſo done, clap a Doſſil into the inferi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our part, that one paſſage may be open, for any bloud, or matter may lodg between, but of that there ſeldom occurreth any: then lay on a common Defenſative, <hi>Ex Bole. Sang. Dracon. Maſtich, Terrae-ſigil.</hi> &amp;c. <hi>cum alb. ovor. &amp; Aceto,</hi> and thereto girt it cloſe with your croſs bandage, and other Compreſſes after their uſual manner: the former, <hi>viz. the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fenſative,</hi> not only defends from accidents: as heat, pain, fluxion, &amp;c. but gently conſtipateth the Veſſels, thereby contributing to the ſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the <hi>Hemorrhage,</hi> and very conſiderably aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſts to the agglutination: the latter, <hi>ſcil.</hi> the Compreſs Ligature, keeps the fleſh ſnug and cloſe to the ends of the divided Veſſels: con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firms the Conſolidation, keeps the parts from Cavity, &amp; the bloud from Extravaſation, and hinders that deflux of humours, which would otherwiſe deſtroy the intention of Cure.</p>
            <p>In this ſort of Amputation, that manner of compreſſing the Thigh by Ligature, or the arm near the ſhoulder, which I have recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended in the foregoing Diſcourſe, is of ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent uſe, becauſe thereby you may reſtrain the deſcent of the bloud, till by your Dreſs and bandage, you have ſo far ſecured the part, as that it can receive no damage thereby.</p>
            <p>In this way of Cure, Phlebotomy, Julaps, Ligature of the extream parts, if need be,
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:106833:71"/>with what elſe may contemperate the bloud, hinder defluxion and maturation, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>motes Conſolidation, though declaimed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt in that Diſcourſe, is in this caſe very uſeful and neceſſary.</p>
            <p>In the ſucceeding Dreſſings, Medicines healing <hi>per ſymphyſin,</hi> are to be uſed; and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt them perhaps there are none better, than that already mentioned, adding ſome powder of the roots of great Comphery thereto; the doſſil if you uſe any, may be left out the next dreſſing, or that following it.</p>
            <p>That this Method hath cured ſuch a ſtump in three weeks, is a truth I can vouch by ſufficient teſtimony, and I believe you will not much doubt it, when you have peruſed this, and conſidered how eaſie, and ſoon ſuch large Conſolidation hath been made; for this, though it be no re-unition, but the conſoli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation of fleſh never before united, will yet be nevertheleſs effected, as is evident in the <hi>coalition of Hair-lips,</hi> the aptitude of the Fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers, Eye-lids, Lips, <hi>glans</hi> and <hi>praeputium,</hi> and the<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>3.</hi> Ob. Med. Chy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rurg. de Clauſura u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teri, ob. <hi>2.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Vagina uteri,</hi> when ulcerate, (of which laſt, <hi>Rhoonhuſe</hi> giveth us a memorable inſtance) to unite, and is alſo more ſtrangely evident, in the ſtories of <hi>Sir</hi>
               <note n="†" place="margin">In the 115 page of his Diſcourſe of the <hi>Sympathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tical Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>K. Dighy,</hi>
               <note n="c" place="margin">Lib. 23. cap. 22.</note> 
               <hi>Amb. Pareus,</hi> and <hi>Taliacotius,</hi> concerning ſupply<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing loſt Noſes, not only by knitting a part of the <hi>homogeneous</hi> arm; but of another mans,
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:106833:71"/>to ſupply the ſcandalous want of that obvi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous part, to which the incomparable Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor of <hi>Hudibras</hi> thus alludeth,</p>
            <q>
               <l>
                  <hi>So learned</hi> Taliacotius <hi>from</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>The brawny part of Porter's Bum,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Cut ſupplemental Noſes, which</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Should laſt as long as parent Breech.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>But —</hi>
               </l>
            </q>
            <p>I muſt not forget to intimate to you, that this manner of diſmembring, &amp;c. is not to be made uſe of, where the part hath been much inflamed, tumified from fluxion, or other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe vexed therewith, nor in members am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putated for Chronick cauſes: as <hi>Cancers, Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtula</hi>'s, &amp;c. or where the body is pockt, or very cachectick, becauſe in ſuch, digeſtion (which would deſtroy the unition) is neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary to rectifie and ſweeten the Maſs, which it doth by draining off the <hi>Miaſma</hi> of the diſeaſe, more than ten <hi>fontanels</hi> can do. It's alſo no leſs unavoidable; for the courſe of matter that hath that way diſcharged it ſelf ſo long, (as in a <hi>Fiſtula</hi>) cannot of a ſudden be obſtructed, without hazard of a miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chievous apoſtumation; moreover in ſuch ill habits, as thoſe caſes either cauſe or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſult from, Conſolidation is difficult, if not im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible to be ſo ſuddenly performed, as this manner of Cure requireth; the <hi>dyſcraſis</hi> of
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:106833:72"/>the bloud having deſtroyed or weakened its Balſam, that it cannot expedite the work, which if not ſpeedily done, cannot be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed ſecurely and firm; and in parts in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flamed and tumified by fluxion, or by con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſtion, it's eaſie to imagine, there muſt be a diſcharge of that concrete matter, which cannot be, and yet the Wound cured by ſym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pathy.</p>
            <p>But in moſt of the Amputations made at Sea in fight, or on Land in Battels, or where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever acute accidents, ſuch as Wounds, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent Lacerations require it, it may be done, and that with thoſe advantages of the other way it Rivals.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt, That it's more ſpeedy;</hi> I mean the Cure, not the Operation: for it effects it in at leaſt one third, or fourth part of the time, that the other method can poſſibly at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chieve it: and of what good uſe this is, both to the Chirurgeon, and Patient, I need not trouble you to mention.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly, Here no dyſepulotick <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>lcer can poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibly happen,</hi> as there frequently doth; eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially to ſtumps of the Legs, when by the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>avoidable prolixity of the cure, ſuch a courſe of matter hath that way diſcharged it ſelf, as cannot afterward be reſtrained, without great trouble and difficulty, if at all.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly, Stumps are this way cured without
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:106833:72"/>ſcaling the bone:</hi> perhaps there is not much trouble, &amp;c. always prevented thereby, as I have already told you, yet ſome there is at all times, and at ſome very much: for inſtance, when Nature is ſlow in caſting off the <hi>Caries,</hi> and the <hi>Hypoſarcoſis</hi> uſually invading ſtumps, about the time of Cicatrization, cover the bone before it ſeparate, ſo that applica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions cannot be made locally, to diſpatch it, which many times proves a great <hi>Remora</hi> to the deſiccation.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fourthly, Here is no expenſive profluence, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of the Radical moiſture, by maturation, and fluxion, or of the bloud by Hemorrhage, or of the Succus nervoſus by a Synovia: or of the lympha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick Liquor, by the lacrymation of thoſe Veſſels:</hi> ill conſequences uſually attending the other Method, and Medicaments.</p>
            <p>I need not prove it, with reſpect to all theſe, they being truths too manifeſt to need it: I ſhall be particular as to the <hi>Hemorrhage,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it may ſeem a ſtrange Aſſertion, that this way ſhould have any advantage of the other, for reſtraining them.</p>
            <p>That it hath ſo, will appear to you, if you pleaſe to conſider, how much more likely it is, that the bleeding Veſſels ſhould be ſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, not only from preſent fluxion, but future <hi>Hemorrhage,</hi> by the ſo cloſe adheſion, and firm unition of fleſh, to that which is circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jacent
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:106833:73"/>to them, and (as may be preſumed, <hi>de facto</hi>) to the ends of the Veſſels themſelves, than by any of the common Methods, or Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicaments I have examined; for that here the Conſolidation is ſo quickly and ſecure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly made, by help of the Application and Ligature, that the divided Veſſel can no more break out, than in cured ſtumps, where they have not only been ſtop'd by any of thoſe common Methods, but covered by the Incarnation and Cicatrix.</p>
            <p>It will ſeem leſs ſtrange, if you further conſider, that after the Ligature of an Arte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, for an <hi>Aneuriſm,</hi> &amp;c. when the Silk rots, or the Veſſel is fretted aſſunder thereby, there is nothing but this incompaſſing fleſh that ſtops it.</p>
            <p>Adding alſo hereto, that the flap which is to cover the ſtump, and ends of the bleed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Veſſels, after Amputation, being of the membranous fleſh; is for the moſt part fatty, and therefore ſometimes called <hi>membrana A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dipoſa:</hi> by which, though it be not ſo apt for Conſolidation, it is the more ſit for ſecuring the flux, becauſe lying upon the ends of the Veſſels, the bloud endeavouring to iſſue from them, cannot penetrate or ſtrain it ſelf through it, as in all probability it would do, in that which were more fibrous, and leſs <hi>pin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gued:</hi> the latter of them being impervious,
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:106833:73"/>the former full of little interſtices: Moreo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, it's by<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Galen. morb. cur.</hi> l. 5. <hi>A. Pareus,</hi> lib. 9. c. 7. Dr. <hi>Read,</hi> Lect. 2.</note> ſome allowed, one way of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraining <hi>Hemorrhagies</hi> to divide the Veſſel, that his bleeding end retiring among the Muſcles, their compreſſure may by cloſing him, ſtop his bleeding; if there be any rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon for that Method, and what it preſumes, it's very conſiderable here.</p>
            <p>No leſs is a more generally allowed Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thod of ſtopping <hi>Hemorrhagies,</hi> viz. by Incar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, that is, by covering the mouths of the divided Veſſels with newly generated fleſh: this Method of the flap, having as much the advantage thereof, as ſuch fleſh whereof it conſiſts, is more firm and fit to do it, than what is newly generated, which is always ſoft and ſpongy.</p>
            <p>Nor is it ridiculous to believe, that recent fleſh, by ſome ſpecifique quality or manner of performance, ſtays <hi>Hemorrhagies,</hi> and that very ſtrangely too, if you believe two no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table Stories delivered by <hi>Felix Platerus in ſunguin. excretione, ob. lib.</hi> 3. the one of a Thief, who by order of Juſtice, having both hands cut off, had the bloud ſtayed.—<hi>Gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum gallinaceum, vivum, interea cultro à podice verus illius ſternum ſcindendo, aperiebat &amp; brachium mutilatum ſtatim poſt ictum, in hane aperturam includebat.</hi>—The other of one that had his Finger bitten away by a Horſe,
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:106833:74"/>
               <hi>Sanguiniſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> fluor, multis fruſtra tentatis non ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteretur:</hi> was cured by the ſame way — <hi>flu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>orque ſtatim ſubſtitit.</hi> —</p>
            <p>But to proceed: <hi>Fifthly, The cure is this way performed with no leſs pain and hazard to the Patient;</hi> the great pain of ſtumps, the watching, <hi>Fever, Convulſions, Syncopes;</hi> the effect of that pain eſpecially at Sea, where neceſſaries are wanting, are here prevented partly from Natures great complacency, and the delight with which ſhe ſeems to co-ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate with Art, in curing <hi>per ſymphyſin:</hi> I ſay, it is that wherewith ſhe not only ſeems pleaſed, but what of her ſelf (as I have al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready ſuggeſted) ſhe will perform, if the lips of the Wound be kept clean, cloſe together, and free from the impreſſions of the Ambi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent Air.</p>
            <p>Partly from her not being put upon the work of digeſtion, or maturation: which (as I have proved) ſhe never performed without a Fever, and perturbation.</p>
            <p>And partly from the nature of the diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent Applications, which are here (as all Ag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glutinatives) Anodyne; whereas thoſe cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red by the other way, muſt indure the heat of Reſtrictives and Digeſtives, the fretting of Detergents to mundifie, and Corroſives to erode, the <hi>Fungus</hi>'s, always occurring more or leſs to Stumps.</p>
            <pb n="119" facs="tcp:106833:74"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Sixthly, It's much eaſier and cheaper to the Chirurgeon:</hi> the firſt, becauſe much ſooner cured, and ſeldomer dreſs'd; the firſt in three weeks, the laſt once a day: the ſecond, for the ſame reaſon, and becauſe fewer Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cines, &amp;c. ſerve at each dreſſing: of what ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage the former is to him when many men are wounded, and eſpecially when diſtant from the eaſe of an Hoſpital, I leave thoſe to tell you that have tryed it, as I have done. The benefit of the latter, conſidering the ſcantineſs of publique allowances, and the great number of men, that may at one time be under Cure, eſpecially in a Mediterranean Voyage, is obvious.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Seventhly, Stumps this way healed, are not obnoxious to break open again on every ſlight rub, or knock,</hi> as do thoſe healed by the other Method, a miſchief they can hardly avoid, though they indeavour it with the greateſt Care and Art; whereas this being fenced with a firm skin, is no more incident to it, than a man's Fingers ends.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Eighthly,</hi> A new and commodious ſort of Artificial Leg, having a Cavity to which the ſtump is to be intruded, and on which the weight of the body, on the alternate mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Legs, muſt be laid, is here moſt tolerable and convenient: whereas the other way, ſcarcely admits the laying the due ſtreſs
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:106833:75"/>on them, by reaſon of the tenderneſs of the ſtump, or its incidency to ſtrip and exco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riate.</p>
            <p>Theſe are all the conſiderable advantages manifeſtly acquired by this new Way, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out doubt, uſe, and tryal, will diſcover more equal to them, and an abundance of leſſer conveniencies, which at preſent occur not to my conſideration; theſe are enough to ſhew the Novelty to be conſiderable, and worthy of imitation: let them have with you this acceſſional manifeſtation, that I am very ready to obey, and ſerve you,</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>Plim.</hi> 
                  <date>
                     <hi>Aug.</hi> 3. 1678.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>James Young.</signed>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:106833:75" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:106833:76"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:106833:77" rendition="simple:additions"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
